<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>New anatomical experiments of John Pecquet of Deip. By which the hitherto unknown receptacle of the chyle, and the transmission from thence to the subclavial veins by the now discovered lacteal chanels of the thorax, is plainly made appear in brutes. As also an anatomical dissertation of the motion of blood and chyle. Together with the further description of the same lacteal chanels newly discovered in the body of man as well as brutes. Being an anatomical historie, publickly propos'd by Thomas Bartoline, Dr. and Reg. Professor both in Physick and Anatomy, to Michael Lysere, answering.</title>
            <author>Pecquet, Jean, 1622-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1521_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1521_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208578</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867520</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170048</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170048)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 194:E1521[1] or 194:E1521[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>New anatomical experiments of John Pecquet of Deip. By which the hitherto unknown receptacle of the chyle, and the transmission from thence to the subclavial veins by the now discovered lacteal chanels of the thorax, is plainly made appear in brutes. As also an anatomical dissertation of the motion of blood and chyle. Together with the further description of the same lacteal chanels newly discovered in the body of man as well as brutes. Being an anatomical historie, publickly propos'd by Thomas Bartoline, Dr. and Reg. Professor both in Physick and Anatomy, to Michael Lysere, answering.</title>
                  <author>Pecquet, Jean, 1622-1674.</author>
                  <author>Bartholin, Thomas, 1616-1680. De lacteis thoracicis et vasis lymphaticiis. English.</author>
                  <author>Lyser, Michael, 1626-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 177, [1]; [4], 127, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.W. for Octavian Pulleyn, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Rose in St. Paul's Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The anatomical history of Thomas Bartholinus" has separate dated title page; pagination and register are separate.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy E.1521[1]: "Octob. 5.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Human anatomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thoracic duct --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Chyle --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Blood --  Circulation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170048:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEW Anatomical Experiments OF <hi>JOHN PECQUET</hi> of DEIP.</p>
            <p>By which the hitherto un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Receptacle of the Chyle, and the Tranſmiſſion from thence to the Subclavial Veins by the now diſcovered Lacteal Chanels of the Thorax, is plainly made appear in Brutes.</p>
            <p>As alſo an Anatomical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertation of the Motion of Blood and Chyle.</p>
            <p>Together with the further De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the ſame Lacteal Chanels newly diſcovered in the Body of Man as well as Brutes.</p>
            <p>Being an Anatomical Hiſtorie, Publickly propos'd by <hi>Thomas Barto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line,</hi> Dr. and <hi>Reg. Profeſſor</hi> both in Phyſick and Anatomy, To <hi>Michael Lyſere,</hi> Anſwering.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. W.</hi> for <hi>Octavian Pulleyn,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Sign of the <hi>Roſe</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170048:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170048:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT to inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that general way of Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, the univerſal and ready reception this late and true diſcovery of our Author, <hi>Pecquet,</hi> hath had, may clearly appear in this, That no Man in all that Croud of Anatomiſts (of whom ſome are onely am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious
<pb facs="tcp:170048:3"/>of being Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory, as more deſiring Controverſy than Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Truth) not any but hath rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd its Verity, than that they would in the leaſt ſeem ignorant of being able to trace thoſe Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, ſo difficult to be found, that the Inventor himſelf durſt, out of juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his good fortune, call it Chance. How this may yet be made clearer, let thoſe that have ſeen what hath followed, be but indifferent Judges.
<pb facs="tcp:170048:3"/>So many able Phyſicians Congratulating his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and as willing to appear Admirers as Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiers of this Truth: One, an approved Doctor both of Phyſick and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, undertakes to make out the benefit and uſe of this Diſcovery, from hence concluding thoſe grand Abſurdities that the Maſters in Phyſick and Chirurgery have ſo many ages laboured under to be onely cleared and made out by this ſo admired Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170048:4"/>
            <p>Another undertakes, with admiration of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to make it his own, without taking notice of our Author, in hope to produce (at leaſt upon ſome) a Confeſſion how much they owe to him for this Diſcovery.</p>
            <p>A Third, an approved Maſter both in Phyſick and Chirurgery, after in his opinion the finiſhing of all that could concern the body of Anatomy, is, as I may ſo ſay, compell'd to ſet Pen to Paper, and by the diſcovery of that in
<pb facs="tcp:170048:4"/>Humane, which our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath done in Brutes, to heap up to himſelf a Fame as laſting as the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (I mean, Man) can be.</p>
            <p>From hence it was I was ſo willing to get this ſo great and new a Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of Anatomy made publick in our own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, my Obſervation being this, That there was no Theater, nay ſcarce any private houſe of ſuch as called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves but pretenders to Anatomy, in which the
<pb facs="tcp:170048:5"/>diſquiſition after this Truth was not labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly proſecuted; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been very well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the Roughneſs at leaſt, if not Crabbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſtile, for a Publick Good, I could do no leſs than to adde what lay in my power to help thoſe weaker per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whoſe Hands are better than their Latine, to a Verity ſo demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable, ſo deſired. I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to teach none, Tranſlation being onely my Deſign; and if any
<pb facs="tcp:170048:5"/>thing may be thought fit to make it perfect, I will not be wanting in the leaſt, ſo far as I am able, to contribute.</p>
            <p>I confeſs it were to be wiſhed that ſome among us of thoſe moſt accurate Obſervers of Natures moſt ſecret Paſſages, would be pleaſed to offer ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of their many Obſervations, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating of ſo beneficial a Truth as this, no Nation, I am confident, having taken more induſtrious Trouble, or greater Charge,
<pb facs="tcp:170048:6"/>in Diſcoveries and Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of Anatomical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments than this our own, Witneſs that great Maſter of Circulation and Generation, Dr. <hi>Harvey.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170048:6"/>
                  <head>The new Anatomick Experiments of the Learned <hi>John Pecquet</hi> of <hi>Diep.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Both <hi>Aſellius</hi> who was the firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverer of the <hi>Milkie Veins</hi> in the Meſentery, and the reſt of the Anatomiſts were ignorant of the place of their meeting. The <hi>Receptacle</hi> of the <hi>Chyle</hi> above the Loyns, and the paſſage from it, not to the Liver, but to the true ſource of blood, the <hi>Heart,</hi> is diſcovered.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE enrichment of the Anatomical Common-wealth by the <hi>Milkie Veins</hi> was the finding, not feigning, of the famous <hi>Aſellius:</hi> But that he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170048:7"/>believes, with the Antients, that the Liver is the ſource of blood, and that the Milkie Veins have their confluence to it, This is [O Reader, if thou canſt behold with thy eyes] his errour. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs beware in the leaſt thou ſtain not the fame of ſo gallant a man; 'Tis not a Little thou oweſt him, who firſt ſearch'd out the unknown turnings of the Chyle, and by whoſe favour thou needs not to walk in darkneſs. <hi>Aſellius</hi> opened it, 'tis enough. The diſcovery is not to be deſpiſed, though never ſo mean. The Beſieged diſcover by the lighteſt repercuſs of a Drum the Ambuſhes of the Enemies Mines; And Star-gazers gather their Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by Shadows.</p>
                     <p>This was the cauſe (except I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake my ſelf) of <hi>Aſellius</hi> his error, That beholding all the Milkie Veins to meet together in that Glandule placed in the middle of the Meſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery [which he cals the <hi>Pancreas</hi>] and from it to be ſtretched upward and downward, he verily believed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170048:7"/>that thoſe branches (which were ſometimes double, ſometimes more, and not ſeeing them concentrate in any place) aſcended to the very fiſſure or cleft of the Liver.</p>
                     <p>Neither ſince that time have any of thoſe [that I know] who in the Anatomick Theatre exerciſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (often, and with great praiſe in living Brutes) endeavoured to trace into any other parts the Milkie liquor of thoſe veins, which even they themſelves did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover.</p>
                     <p>And indeed the learned <hi>Wallaeus</hi> in his Epiſtles to <hi>Th. Bartoline</hi> ſaith, <hi>By theſe Milkie Veins the Chyle goeth upward: but by what means it doth ſo, is a matter more intricat. This ſeems to me to be moſt likely, which I have taken notice of in great and lean Hounds, That ſome of the Milkie Veins with one and a continued paſſage have entred into the Meſenterick-Branch, ſome into the very</hi> Vena porta, <hi>ſome into the hollowneſs of the Liver, and a very ſmall number
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170048:8"/>ſometimes into the</hi> Vena cava <hi>near the Emulgents.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So conclude the moſt skilful Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, <hi>Harvey, Veſling, Conringe, Bartoline,</hi> and many other; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth <hi>Riolane</hi> himſelf think better (which is marvelous in reſpect of the mans excellent quickneſs and ſharpneſs of wit whereby he hath gone before all others in Anatomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſſection) hear his Opinion of this matter in the XVIII Chapter of his <hi>Encheirid.</hi> This one diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of diſtribution, ſaith he, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth many; For in a living full and opened Beaſt, thoſe Milkie Veins are ſeen ſpread indeed in the Meſentery, and ſome of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the <hi>Pancreas,</hi> ſome to the Liver, others are derived to the trunck of the <hi>Vena Cava,</hi> but none of them go to the Spleen, neither do they after the manner of the <hi>Vena porta</hi> run together in one ſtem.</p>
                     <p>I, by the leave of ſo great men, would ſay that not any of them by a particular inqueſt have ſearched the Lurkings of theſe Lacteal Veins
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170048:8"/>within the Thorax. But I believe this is rather to be attributed to their misfortune than negligence, becauſe none of them knew that the Chyle was not derived to the Liver, nor to the <hi>Vena porta,</hi> nor to the <hi>Vena cava</hi> near the Emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, as the received errour held forth: but, which in diſſection may be ſeen to any man more clear than the light, <hi>From the Guts to a certain RECEPTACLE</hi> of that bigneſs, which will full up the <hi>interſtitium</hi> between the <hi>Lumbar Muſcles,</hi> at leaſt in Beaſts.</p>
                     <p>Now this receptacle above the Vertebers of the Loyns receives the Liquor of the Milkie veins ſpread in the Meſentery, and rendreth it again by thoſe Milkie Veins, which being hid within the breaſt, in a continued paſſage run to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clavial venal branches, till within the aſcending ſtem of the <hi>Vena cava</hi> about the External Jugulars, being mixt with the blood, and running in one and the ſame Chanel, it throws its ſelf headlong into the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170048:9"/>Whirlpool of the <hi>Heart,</hi> there to receive its <hi>purple dye</hi> &amp; preparation for alimentary ſubſtance; As might be evinced by that noble Teſtimony the Prince of the Peripateticks hath aſſerted, That <hi>the Heart is the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of the Veins, and Forge of the Blood.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Chyle being found on the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of the Heart and <hi>Vena cava,</hi> is diſcovered to be convey'd thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Subclavian Branches; And the Inſertion thereof is plainly perceived at the concourſe of the Axillar and Jugular Veins.</head>
                     <p>BEware (O Reader) and think not that thou oweſt to me the Originations of theſe Milkie Veins, or the Original of this my deſign: No, it was the gift of Fortune ſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with me altogether ignorant. But to uſe good words, and ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Chriſtian, It was the great
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170048:9"/>gift of Providence, which is God, revealing it to me imprudent. And leſt by any Claim the duty of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs ſhould be intermitted, It ſeems good to me for the praiſe of him that is Strong and Zealous, to ſet down plainly the whole Hiſtorie of my happineſs, if indeed it be as pleaſant for thee to hear, as me to rehearſe it.</p>
                     <p>After I had ſome years ago, by Cutting up of Dead Bodies, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd a dumb (I may ſay) and cold Knowledge, I reſolved to ſqueez forth true knowledge from the Harmonie yea of twenty Living Creatures. And becauſe theſe differ from the former almoſt onely in Motion, which hath its chief ſeat in the Heart, It was my purpoſe, having uncloathed and cut out the Heart, to contemplate it more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly.</p>
                     <p>Therefore having cloven aſunder the Thorax of a Great Hound, I begun my view of the contained parts without delay; I pluckt out the Heart, having cut aſunder thoſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170048:10"/>Veſſels wherewith it was tied to the reſt of the body; The abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of blood, which immediately flow'd, did at preſent ſtop my pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fight; that being ſpent, I did wonder to ſee flowing in the Pipe of the <hi>Vena cava</hi> at its connection to the right Ventricle a milkie liquor, caſting it ſelf out by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
                     <p>The remaining drops of the blood had ſtain'd its colour, ſo that I ſuſpected by the firſt view of it that it was Pus diſcharged from ſome apoſtumation lurking (may be) within the breaſt: But when the Heart being altogether pluck'd from its place, and placed on the Table, had almoſt with equal ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency contracted it ſelf into ninety Syſtoles, and in as many Diaſtoles dilated it ſelf, and with a little palpitation had brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed forth its laſt ſpirits, I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of my former thought, nor could longer think that ſo great a diſeaſe could be neighbour to ſo grand a vigour.</p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170048:10"/>
                     <p>Therefore having perfected my deſign, and peruſed all the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contained parts which offered themſelves fair and ſound, as alſo the whole Thorax, I did open the <hi>Vena cava</hi> from the Diaphragm unto the Throat. Immediately there appeared a little ſtream of that Liquor I doubted of, not ſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any mixture of blood.</p>
                     <p>From the Subclavian Branches unto the Pericardium within the Vein there ſetled down a very white Liquor, moſt like the Chyle ſpread abroad in the Meſentery; ſo that they being compared together, both their colour, ſmell, taſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence ſhew there was no difference betwixt them.</p>
                     <p>The motion of the embowelled Beaſt ceaſing, that alſo did ſtop its flowing; neither did the reſt ſuffer me to know whence or from what place that Milkie ſtream had its riſe: Nevertheleſs inflamed with the deſire of the concealed Myſterie, I preſt the Thymus, I bound the neck, and I diſquieted all the limbs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170048:11"/>of the foreparts, if any where per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance the reſidue of that whitiſh ſubſtance would diſtil out of its winding veſſels: But from thence onely came ſome drops of blood, and not the leaſt Milkie ſubſtance appeared in the <hi>Vena cava.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore [that which onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained to ſhew my induſtry] I go about to demonſtrate what part of this matter the Milkie Veins of the Meſentery might have by preſſing them with the weight of my finger. They yield to my perſute: for out of the Subclaval-branches ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of the juice I had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved did flow, that I both knew the Milkie Veins to be the ſource thereof, and did eſteem it a great madneſs to hold this to differ from the Chyle.</p>
                     <p>Leſt any thing nevertheleſs ſhould be left unattempted, ſeeing from the upper parts of thoſe Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the matter did ruſh down, I cleft the Veins of the neck, and all other the fore-parts; and preſſing the capacity of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170048:11"/>the belly immediately where it ſwelleth below, and turning my ſight to thoſe opened Chanels near the Claviculars, behold to the accompliſhment of my wiſhes, the Chyle did flow abundantly in the upper parts of the Subclavicular-branches on both ſides.</p>
                     <p>I noted alſo ſmall Valves cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe minute perforations, or rather inſertions, places moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the beholders, <hi>viz.</hi> little holes gaping with as little Valves, a little below the Cataracts or meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together of the Jugular and Axillar: Veins: But there alſo I did obſerve the little Valves of the Jugular Veins, altogether to ſtop the eaſy aſcent of the Chyle, which would otherwiſe fall into the deep pool of the Heart. But indeed I could not demonſtrate by what way, by what paſſages the Chylus was conveyed thither, by reaſon of the emptied Meſentery of the Beaſt long ago dead, the Milkie Veins alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vaniſhing with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed liquor.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170048:12"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The double way of the Milkie Veins diſcovered within the Breaſt, from the diſcharge of the Chyle into the Subclavian Veins down to the fourth Verteber of the back; beyond which inſertion there is no Twig of the Milkie-Veins ſtretched to the upper parts.</head>
                     <p>I Had immediately in the place of the dead dog another which unexpectedly was offered to me by accident, but his leanneſs ſeemed to foretell the emptineſs of his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteal veins through his long hunger. Therfore I went about to cram this hunger-ſtarv'd Dog; when at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of thoſe, whom the newneſs of the matter had invited to the ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, I did unbowel the hungry Beaſt.</p>
                     <p>Then it clearly appeared, which I told thoſe that did urge me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably; for the Stomack with the guts were ſo miſerably empty, that not any ſhew of the Lacteal veins in any place, yea not in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170048:12"/>Meſentery, did remain to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the eyes of any of the beholders.</p>
                     <p>Immediately their haughty auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity did reproach my buſy cenſure, and did deny any faith to things not appearing. I, when I did ſee the moſt, I might ſay all of them, to give no credit to me (by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible geſture) for all I could argue; Well [ſaid I to my ſelf] at laſt you have learned to uſe your eyes: But, 'tis juſt that theſe ſame eyes, whoſe loathing winks I obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with willing ſervice, be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in you hereafter with a ſtedfaſt beholding, as with an unavoydable ſcourge, and iterated inſpection of the intrails.</p>
                     <p>I had foretold truly to thoſe that raſhly haſtned the unſeaſonable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection, that the Pipes of the Lacteal veins were moſt ſlender, and onely remarkable by the whiteneſs of the Liquor they convey; which juice, whether it follow the upſucking Diaſtoles of the Heart, or which is more likely, it ruſheth forward by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170048:13"/>the incitement of ſome impulſive cauſe afterwards to be enquired of, it maketh a very little ſtay in its paſſing. In vain is the Chanel ſought, when the fulneſs of the Fountain faileth. Neither is Chyle procreated by faſting, neither is meat preſently after the eating thereof converted into that nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubſtance.</p>
                     <p>Therefore, not being hindred by any mans command, I brought the inſnared Dog under my diet; and when I had refreſhed his long faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with abundance of meat, again about the fourth hour after his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we addreſt our ſelves to the examining of his Entrails.</p>
                     <p>Our chief purpoſe was, not to obſerve the Lacteal veins, which we beheld with infinite flowing rillets ſtreaming in all places through the Meſentery, but with all our endeavours to pry into the Thorax.</p>
                     <p>The Heart there untouched did unfold its Syſtoles; the reſt of the Lifes Inſtruments which are near
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170048:13"/>to the Heart, did each accompliſh its own duty. Neither as yet being reſolved to offer violence to any, I turned back the Lungs, being lifted by the ſtedfaſt hand of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, from the right ſide towards the cavity of the left, that I might view all the ſecret-rooms of the back.</p>
                     <p>I beheld the branches of the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> all were livid; no branch of the aſcending Arteries was diſcovered near the Milkie holes I had lately found out: I followed the ſprules of the Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pars, whereof theſe were ſtopt by the oppoſition of the Diaphragm, other ſwallowed up of the lower belly. At laſt turning my ſight to the higheſt ſides of the Vertebers of the Back, I know not what whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſs, like to a pipe of Chyle, ſtaid mine eyes, it creeping for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a little, with crooked turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings cloſe to the back-bone; by the ſhape of it I doubted whether it was a Nerve, or that Veſſel which I with all care had enquired
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170048:14"/>after. Therefore tying a ligature a little below the Clavicles, I imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly perceived that it emptied it ſelf, and became flaccid above the Ligature, and below a tumor not onely remaining, but rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing by reaſon of the Flux of the matter, my doubt was then ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.</p>
                     <p>But becauſe Miſtakes in this kind produce as erroneous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, I durſt not yet paſs a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory ſentence, by mine eyes which were witneſſes of ſo evident a matter; I enquire alſo into the left ſide, there alſo a brother-conduit to the right ſide did ſtray up and down, who likewiſe being bound up as the other, by the ſame event confeſſed himſelf to be a ducture of the ſame kind; I haſtned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to divide theſe Veſſels, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous through the middle of the <hi>Pleura,</hi> from the reſt of their fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts of the breaſt, with my ſharp Knife: The unexhauſted neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-head of the untoucht Heart did overflow my work with a bloody in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170048:14"/>But the Heart immediatly being pulled out, was both puniſhed for its troubling the work, and removed all obſtacles of its further continuance.</p>
                     <p>After the Blood was ſpung'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, from both the Ligatures, and the <hi>Pleura</hi> being removed, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the Milkie-Canals to the Throat. From the third Verteber of the Back, where they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the ſociety of their upholder the back-bone, adhering to the <hi>Oeſophagus</hi> under which they win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly did creep, hither and thither did they proceed to the Clavicles themſelves; firmly leaning on the <hi>Thymum,</hi> in a fourfold or more nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous ſtream they enter the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clavian Veins: I beheld theſe Veins with moſt covetous eyes being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſplit aſunder; when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold again through theſe little holes found out about the Jugulars, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatures being untyed, on both ſides a Milkie rivolet did pour forth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly Chyle into the <hi>Vena cava.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But then the Spectators contempt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170048:15"/>repenting at the miracle, by their encouragement it was impoſed on me to ſearch out whether any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Conduit of the Chyle did go to the Head, or was derived to the Fore-limbs. But when I had cut off the head, and diſ-membred the limbs, no Milk did follow, no not by preſſing the Inferiour belly. Now from that abundance of Chyle which emptied it ſelf into the <hi>Vena Cava,</hi> I argue, that the Chyle nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther runneth to the Head or Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limbs, but altogether floweth into the Subclaval Branches.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The double way of the Lacteal Veins is cleared from the fourth Verteber of the Back to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Diaphragm.</head>
                     <p>MY hope did grow by fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate events, and my toyl was forgiven to my proſperous la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. The diſcovered Door im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned me to ſearch the Gallery.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170048:15"/>I return to the Ligatures; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bound them near the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſides of the third Verteber of the Back, now I certainly follow downward the ſwelling Milkie-Veins.</p>
                     <p>About the fourth Verteber, which is the ſeat of the Heart, they were hid under the gullet; I then did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingage this gullet, being tyed with all the reſt of the vital parts, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my amputation near the Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicles; Yea the <hi>Aorta</hi> alſo which I had ſpared, thinking it would not ſhadow it, cutting gently the branches which are interlaced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ribs, upon that account that it was an hindrance, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to depart the Cavity of the Thorax; and having removed all impediments of the remaining engagements, you might behold o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, without doubting eyes, the whole courſe of the Milkie-ſtreams along the higheſt platform of the Back-bone.</p>
                     <p>The fourth Verteber did uphold their joyning together, the reſt of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170048:16"/>the ſpace to the tenth Verteber up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held them parted in two and divided with winding turnings like to Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. They did flow with like ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, not ſeldome with traverſe trenches, as it were for mutual help obliquely tyed together. At length in a common Chanel, and again in divided ſtreams by little and little growing into emboſſed billows, do ſwell up at the Center of the Diaphragm; not a ſlender token of the near fountain from whence the Chyle through the breaſt flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the Subclavian veins.</p>
                     <p>Therefore when I went about to ſeparate the Diaphragm it ſelf from the Lacteal Veſſels, that it might not hinder my laſt (which I hoped for) ſearch, the ſwelling billow of the Veſſel being torn on the left ſide near the twelfth Verteber of the back, whoſe tunicle is very thin, wondring at the abundance of the poured-out milk there harboured, I ſuſpected there was not a little <hi>Receptacle</hi> of that Liquor hid there. But the unwarineſs of my hand
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170048:16"/>ſtopt my progreſs, and made me throw away the reſt of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe as uſeleſs; for the outflowing of the Chyle altogether emptied the Lacteals, and the remaining pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licle of the vaniſhing tumor, where it ſeemed to grow in billows, the Ventricle (as they ſay) thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cut could promiſe no happy event to my further Inqueſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170048:17"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The Receptacle of the Chyle till this day unknown, is ſearched af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. 'Tis demonſtrated that the Chyle floweth not towards the Liver, neither the Lacteal-veins tend thither. The Receptacle of the Chyle is diſcovered under the Center of the Meſentery. This receives the Chyle from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of <hi>Aſellius</hi> his Lacteals. <hi>Aſellius</hi> his <hi>Pancreas</hi> is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in all, nor the ſame, neither one. The Milkie Veins lack not their own Valves through the Breaſt.</head>
                     <p>HAving fed a Dog abundantly with fitting diet, a few hours after his repaſt, I placed him on the Anatomical Theatre. The firſt Exerciſe onely opened his Breaſt: Neither made I any ſtay, but ſtopping on both ſides the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trances of the Lacteals beneath the Clavicles by a Ligature, I prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Chyles eſcape. Pulling away
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170048:17"/>the ſtops of the ſtaying parts, I haſtned my progreſs; And to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the belly which ſtraitned the Cavity of the Thorax, I made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion from thence clean through the <hi>Abdomen,</hi> according to its longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and by this means expoſed to view the whole Cavity of the Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax.</p>
                     <p>I had not long time to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the Siſterly-Lacteal rivolets, not differing in much from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. My young-grown ſuſpition of a Receptacle urged me by degrees into a mindful belief, that the lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place was by all tokens evinced to be beyond the Diaphragm, hid under the Center of the Meſentery. Neither would I have delayed by the deſtruction of the reſiſting En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails to have unlocked the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, except that old Error of Sanguification now laſt of all had not troubled my mind, even hardly departing from her former prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
                     <p>Until this Time, Opinion, not Truth, thruſt the Chyle from the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170048:18"/>Meſentery into the ſubſtance of the Liver, and did attribute the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved privilege of Sanguifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that Entrail provided by Nature for another uſe. I with exact diligence did examine all the branches going thither, each by it ſelf, whether the Chyle run through any of them to that place. I on every ſide did ſeek out the Milkie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillets, and found none of them to be ſtretched to the Liver; I cleft the <hi>Vena-porta,</hi> I opened the Sple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick-paſſage, neither did I ſpare the Meſentery it ſelf, except in ſo far as the riſing tumor of the Milkie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veins appearing white through the Meſentery, ſeemed to allow; which my careful fear of the evaniſhing Chyle did preſerve, being mindful of the <hi>Receptacle.</hi> I diſcovered the Center of the <hi>Vena-cava,</hi> not onely where it enters the Emulgents, but even from the Iliacks to the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragm; and from all parts no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing flowed but Blood, no ſpring of Chyle did in the leaſt colour this falſe-believed paſſage.</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170048:18"/>
                     <p>Neither [O Reader] truſt thou to mine eyes, which I uſed moſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently in a matter of ſo great weight: There are Witneſſes, no more friends to me than to the truth, which beheld it, and whoſe ſcornful laughter I rather feared, than hoped their pardon, if I had ſtuck in the matter. Thou thy ſelf enter the Liſts, ſeeing long ago I have rouſed up and challenged thy ſpirit to ſo brave atchievements. He is a ſluggard who for fear of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour hath all his faith in his ears; neither is he worthy of wiſdome, who follows that errour whereof he may undeceive himſelf.</p>
                     <p>The truth being unſhel'd by ſo great teſtimonies, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Chyle did not flow to the Liver, nor to the <hi>Vena-porta,</hi> neither to the <hi>Vena-cava</hi> near the Emulgents; Upon this View of the Entrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s we were commanded by the Chyle to ſeek ſome other place of the lower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt belly by which this diſcharge of Chyle was to be protruded out into the Thorax. The fruitfulneſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170048:19"/>of the Milkie-veins did keep the Meſentery from falling; I diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the turgid veins, and made them fall flat by tying Ligatures about the Baſis thereof. Then by piece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal, to be more wary, taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Diaphragm, you might ſee clearly the reſidue of the Trunk of the <hi>Aorta,</hi> that lurked under the productions thereof, together with our Lacteal-veins.</p>
                     <p>Theſe likewiſe on the left ſide, under that part of the <hi>Aorta</hi> which ſendeth forth the Phrenetick-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, did unfold their ſwelling Chanels, below both ſides running into one ſtream, ſeeming to grow into a ſwelling lake of Chyle. And then, my eyes allowing the touch its part, by preſſing with my fore-finger I oft tried on each part the eſcape of the encloſed liquor: There, which is wonderful! the paſſage did render it ſelf flat to the compreſſing finger; The ſoftneſs coming by jumps did argue a blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not of ſmall capacity to hold Chyle lurking under the Center of the Meſentery.</p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170048:19"/>
                     <p>At laſt, I cut with a ſparing Knife all the hiding tunicles; Such a bladder I eſpied, not divorced from the <hi>Aorta,</hi> but as it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into its protection, under the Coeliack ſtern and Emulgent bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, neither altogether lurking, nor altogether appearing: So at laſt was laid open that moſt deſired ſtorehouſe of the Chyle, and that <hi>Receptacle</hi> ſearched out by my ſo much labour.</p>
                     <p>This was ſtretched downward from the Diaphragm upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minences of the Vertebers of the Lower belly, even to the third Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teber of the Loyns or thereabouts; here and there it did adhere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Kidneys to thoſe emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Kernels or Caſes, which are called Atribilar Grandules; being kept in below with the Dams of the Lumbar muſcles on both ſides, it did occupy the whole ſpace in the middle, but with a furrow ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing inclining to the right ſide.</p>
                     <p>But whence comes ſo great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of Nouriſhment? I ſay, by what Chanels doth the Chylous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170048:20"/>liquor run into that Lake drain'd by its continual gliding through the breaſt? I long ago ſuſpected the Meſenteries diligence, and chiefly that neighbouring tumor of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteal veins therein, which was believed by me to diſgorge into this Receptacle the nouriſhment they received from the Guts. The dawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of truth, which are ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, ſuffered me not any longer to be toſs'd in theſe miſts of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture.</p>
                     <p>Therefore immediately the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle of the <hi>Receptacle</hi> being torn, the Chyle ran forth; and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the cleft of the ſame wound the Chyle, which I had ſet free, by looſing my tyes in the turgid La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteals of the Meſentery, by its evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſpringing out removed all my doubts.</p>
                     <p>The knowledge of this <hi>Recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> evaniſhing altogether with the Chyle, being mindful again of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellius,</hi> turning over the middle of the Meſentery, I ſearch for that great Glandule he ſaith is placed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170048:20"/>there; but the abſence thereof did altogether diſ-appoint my labour. For, for the moſt part Domeſtick Beaſts want that Glandule, or at leaſt you ſhall ſee it to fall into many diſtinct little ones, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times divided into five, as <hi>Walleus</hi> hath obſerved before me.</p>
                     <p>The Meſentery of the Beaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing viewed, preſented three, placed at a manifeſt diſtance one from the other: They were adjacent to the Emulgents, one of them to the right Emulgents, being of a more longiſh figure; The reſt lay near the left, with a more round body, more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting a Globe.</p>
                     <p>It is, my reſolution to diſcover the uſe of theſe, and of <hi>Aſellius</hi> his <hi>Pancreas,</hi> wherever 'tis found. While the Meſentery ſwels with turgid Lacteals, a part of the Chyle is poured into the hollow boſomes of theſe Glandules; which is clear not onely by the many Conduits of the Milkie veins encompaſſing them like Spider-webs; but alſo their ſhedding of Chyle if you cut them
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170048:21"/>up. Indeed the Meſentery having unburthened the Lacteal veins, the Chyle alſo is then poured out of the Glandules into the <hi>Receptacle</hi> by the lower, yet more ample pipes: From which the flowing again back to the Meſentery [as doth evidently appear by the turgidneſs of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle</hi> when the Meſentery is quite taken away] is ſtopt by the forbidding Valves: There remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely in the Glandules a rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of ſerous liquor, which I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem the ſpongious Glandules have onely drunk up, being ſuperfluous to the paſſing aliment, as a reward of their hoſpitality.</p>
                     <p>I would have ſacrificed, if the double Veſſels of the Lacteals ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Vertebers of the Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax, had not by their conſtantly whitiſh tumor called back my wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring eyes to their view. The ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their paſſages with a Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture about the third Verteber of the back, had raiſed up their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels downward; neither did they, while the Meſenterick Lacteals
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170048:21"/>emptied themſelves of their Milkie ſubſtance through the torn paſſage of the <hi>Receptacle,</hi> at all change into a ſmaller ſtream, or throw out their Chyle.</p>
                     <p>Therefore when I preſſed back again the full Conduits with the force of my fore-finger, the little Valves lurking in the knotty veins did diſ-appoint this my laſt labour, not without a moſt delectable te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of their preſence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170048:22"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Not onely a Dog, but other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Beaſts have their Milkie Veins and Receptacle; and 'tis ſhewn 'tis not lacking in man. The Teſtimonies of Grave men are called to witneſs the truth of this Book.</head>
                     <p>THus (good Reader) you have the exact Hiſtorie of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteal Conduits. Within the courſe of three Diſſections I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the continual work of almoſt three years; becauſe by the loſs of ſo little a time, you may be delivered from errour. The cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of three Dogs will afford thee that which was ſcarcely at length granted to me by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowelling of more than a hundred living Beaſts.</p>
                     <p>Neither believe thou I was onely convinced of this by the evidence of prying into the intrails of Hounds: All kind of Beaſts almoſt vindicates alſo to it ſelf this Glory
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170048:22"/>of the ſhewen Chylous Conduit: Kine, Horſe, Swine, and not a few of other ſorts being offered, did ſtain with their blood my inciſion-knife.</p>
                     <p>Nature onely ſports it ſelf for a while in Sheep: In theſe not a double Conduit, but one Pipe alone doth carry the Chyle from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle to the fourth Verteber of the back, and thence cleft in two waies it unburthens it ſelf into the <hi>Vena cava</hi> by theſe little Valves in the Subclavian holes, as hath been ſhewn in a Dog. I have obſerved the ſame, but ſeldomer, in other Beaſts: but howſoever the Chyle deſireth ſhort waies, and ſhuns the multitude of paſſages, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding from the ſame ſtarting off at the Receptacle, it endeth its courſe at the ſame mark of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars.</p>
                     <p>I ſpake not of Men, becauſe I abominate the Thoantean Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, being inur'd to a more meek devotion. I did not ſpare Beaſts who were fram'd by the Creator
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170048:23"/>for the uſe of Man. I honoured the Living Creature which was more holy than theſe: The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of that inbred Law, which I adore, abſtained from this; his health is my ſcope, and not that that is to him moſt fearful. That Medicine is to be ſhunned that Cruelty doth teach, and that Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be abhorred that Murther produceth.</p>
                     <p>Nevertheleſs I boldly affirm, That alſo Men, whom the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Parent hath indued with the ſame burthen of intrails with Beaſts, have not a different ſtorehouſe of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſubſtance. This [leſt you ſhould ſcorn our opinion, as Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt in the very Haven by our lack of Experience] beſides the long continuance of the Lacteal veins in the humane Carcaſe, obſerved by <hi>Tulpius</hi> in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> by <hi>Veſlin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> in <hi>Padua,</hi> and <hi>Folius</hi> in <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> is proved by the famous Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of that worthy <hi>Gaſſendus,</hi> which affirms that the Illuſtrious <hi>Peireſchius</hi> did behold in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentery
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170048:23"/>of a Thief opened a little after his execution, the Veins tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid with Milk. Writing his Life he thus proceeds: Wherefore <hi>Pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchius</hi> did procure, that before the ſentence of death ſhould be pronounced againſt the perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to be hang'd, he ſhould be ſecurely and well fed, that there might be matter for abundance of Chyle againſt that time he ſhould ſearch for it; and thence within an hour and a half after he was hanged, and the body commanded to be brought unto the Anatomick Theatre, it was performed with ſo great diligence, that the Belly being immediately opened, the white Veins did appear, So that from ſome of them, being opened, you might have gathered a Milkie li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, which indeed ſeemed very wonderful. <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> himſelf was preſent at this ſpectacle, which he told me long ago with his own mouth, whilſt he lived in <hi>Paris.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And becauſe that is not good which deſires not to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170048:24"/>I brought many, not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon men, not out of the dregs of the people; but men Learned, and much ſeen in Anatomical mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: That, being rather partners of my happineſs, than witneſſes of my knowledge, they might at leaſt by their authority compel you to venture on the matter.</p>
                     <p>It pleaſeth me by ſome of their pickt-out names to overthrow the obſtinateneſs [if yet it remain] of your mind. In the mouth of two or three Witneſſes every word is juſtified, ſaith the holy Oracles. I will produce more. And amongſt the firſt indeed <hi>James Mentellus,</hi> a Patrician, and famous Profeſſour of Phyſick in the College of <hi>Paris,</hi> and his moſt worthy Grand-child unto whom the World oweth the Invention of <hi>PRINTING.</hi> Then <hi>Peter Merſennus,</hi> a Learned Doctor of the ſame faculty. I will adde <hi>Adrian Auzot</hi> of <hi>Roan,</hi> a man indued with all ſorts of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by whoſe help, advice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate friendſhip, not a few things
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170048:24"/>were diſcovered to me. I would have wiſhed that <hi>Ludovick Gayan,</hi> the famous Chirurgian, whoſe great skill I admired while he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſected in the Publick Phyſick-Schools of <hi>Paris,</hi> and the noble <hi>Mentellus</hi> read the Lecture, ſhould either be the Condemner of my Errours, or Aſſertor of that Truth manifeſted to me by ſo many Experiments. Neither would I have paſſed by, if Death too ſoon had not envied, <hi>James Duval,</hi> a moſt skilful Doctor of the ſame faculty in <hi>Paris,</hi> who ingenuouſly was long ago a Herald of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered verity, as the love to the ſame made him a moſt diligent ſpectator of my Experiments.</p>
                     <p>I will not ſpeak more of theſe men, leſt by the unpoliſhed rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my ſpeech I prejudice them. I would likewiſe produce more, but the faith of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes is ſuſpected where a few and ſo famous do not ſuffice. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the mind of him that judgeth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170048:25"/>free of unbelief, if he will have, beyond the Laws appointment, the number multiplied of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170048:25"/>
                  <head>The Expoſition of the Figures.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Firſt Figure</hi> ſheweth the Milkie Veſſels found within the Breaſt, together with the <hi>Recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> of the Chyle, by themſelves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the cut-up Beaſt.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A.</hi> The Aſcendent Trunk of the <hi>Vena cava</hi> opened all along upwards.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>BB.</hi> The meeting together of the Jugular and Axillar Veins, where the ſpringing out of the Chyle into the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> or the little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trances of the Lacteal Conduits, are marked with points.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CC.</hi> The Valves of the Jugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ſtopping the aſcent of the Chyle running into the <hi>Vena cava.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>DD.</hi> The diſtributions of the Milkie Conduits at their ſpringings into the Veins.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>EE.</hi> The divers meetings of the Lacteal Veſſels at the appointment of ſporting Nature.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>F.</hi> The Bottle or Billow which oft hath appeared within the breaſt on the left ſide near the uncut Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragm.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>G.</hi> The Chanel on the right ſide ſwelling greater.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170048:26"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>HH.</hi> The portion of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragm which remaineth.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I.</hi> The RECEPTACLE of the Chyle.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>LLL.</hi> The ſtems of the Meſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terick Lacteal Veins; the greater Tunicles of theſe near the <hi>Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle</hi> ſignifieth there are Valves pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced there to hinder the reflux of the Chyle.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>MMM.</hi> Divers Valves within the breaſt giving paſſage to the Chyle to the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> but ſtopping its return to the <hi>Receptacle.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Second Figure</hi> demonſtrateth an open Dog with the Veſſels ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the <hi>Firſt Figure,</hi> as each one in his proper place is ſituate in the Beaſt.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> The Aſcendent Trunk of the <hi>Vena cava.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> The part of the Aorta re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining betwixt the Kidneys, ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Receptacle of the Chyle.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3 3.</hi> The Kidneys.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4 4.</hi> The cut-up Diaphragm.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5 5.</hi> The Muſcles of the Loyns, called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170048:26"/>
                  <p>AN <hi>Anatomical Diſſertation</hi> Concerning the CIRCULATION OF THE BLOOD, AND MOTION OF THE CHYLE.</p>
                  <p>By JOHN PECQUET.</p>
                  <p>Printed in the Year 1653.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170048:27"/>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170048:27"/>
                  <head>An Anatomical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertation concerning the Circulation of the Blood, and Motion of the Chyle.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <head>The ſum of the Diſſertation.</head>
                     <p>The Circular motion of the Blood through the whole body of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creature is demonſtrated; the cauſe of that motion is ſhewn; the opinion of <hi>Attraction</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by Water-works; the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the <hi>Chyle</hi> out of the <hi>Guts</hi> into the <hi>Milkie Veins</hi> is ſet forth, and the <hi>Straining-office</hi> of the <hi>Liver</hi> is aſſerted.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE proſperous ſucceſs of the diſcovered paths in which the Chyle is carried, by the former Experiments, is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement ſtirring up the bold
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170048:28"/>endeavour of a confident mind to make inqueſt wither it ruſheth. But becauſe the commerce which the Lacteals have with the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Vena cava</hi> ſhew the Chyle is tributary to the Blood; 'Tis moſt fitting that the Superiours motion be conſidered in the moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble place, before the Vaſſals courſe come in view.</p>
                     <p>Here then we will firſt conclude, That the Blood ruſhing into the Arteries by the impulſe of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoles, and returning again by the crooked ſmall paſſages of the Veins even into the boſome of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoles, is circulated in the whole body, as is proved by the teſts of Experience, and ſo returned into the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> as alſo by the reflowing motion of the <hi>Vena porta.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Next we will reaſon concerning the beginning of this motion, chiefly againſt thoſe who attribute the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the Blood, ſhed out of the Arteries into the Veins, and ſo into the Ventricles of the Heart, unto
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170048:28"/>the attracting Diaſtole; and the Myſteries of Pneumatical or Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works whereby they advance <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction</hi> are diſcovered; So that by the touchſtone of Experience it ſhall be cleared, That the Water followeth the Clack in a Pump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe not onely by the weight of the air which compreſſeth the Globe of Earth-water, but likewiſe by the Elatere of the Air, that is, by its Spontaneous dilatation, or extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf of its own accord: As alſo that the ſame Air in an <hi>Aeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipilas</hi> or Wind-gun that is thruſt hard together; and that in Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows are heaped up, and that in Fleſh doth protuberate in Cupping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſſes.</p>
                     <p>Afterwards we will demonſtrate a threefold incitement of the ſame motion in the Blood: For [good Reader] the Syſtole doth not onely ſtir up the Blood; There is alſo a natural quality in the greater Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, according to the meaſure of their capacity. Adde to this at leaſt the Elaſtick or extended bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170048:29"/>of the adjacent weight either of the preſſure in Reſpiration, or of the Muſcular Contraction.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, having by the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments held forth the motion of the ſtream of the Chyle, we will demonſtrate with all clearneſs poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible the <hi>Tranſcolatory</hi> or ſtraining uſe of the Liver, appointing with <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the Gall for the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Blood.</p>
                     <div n="1" type="chapter">
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The motion of the Blood from the Heart by the Arteries to the Extremities of the Body, and from the Extremities by the Veins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the Heart, is aſſerted by Experiments.</head>
                        <p>THat I might try whether the Blood flowed by the Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, I tyed ſtrait with a thread the Artery ſometime of the fore-foot, ſometime of the hind-foot, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the Carotidals, leſt any thing ſhould eſcape me, in a living Dog.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170048:29"/>The Artery in a ſhort time beyond the Ligature, <hi>viz.</hi> towards the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of the Body, falling, and riſing on this ſide; I mean betwixt it and the Heart, by reaſon of the obſtructed ſtream, doth teach that the Blood is carried from the Heart by the Arteries unto the Extremities of the Body.</p>
                        <p>But leſt (Reader) thou ſhouldſt accuſe my inference of Lightneſs, the Artery being cloven beyond the Ligature, yea to take away thy cavelling, being quite cut off, did ſcarcely ſtain the wound with Blood; when being opened on this ſide the Ligature, it burſt forth in a ſpring of Blood.</p>
                        <p>Having examined the Arteries, I reſolved to view the courſe of the Blood in the <hi>Vena cava:</hi> This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freed from its Teguments, I bound it in the ſame place, ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving its Fellow-Artery free: But with a ſucceſs directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the other; for on this ſide the band towards the Heart it fell, and roſe beyond the Ligature to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170048:30"/>the Extremities of the Body: Then being wounded in that place that was flaccid, it emitted no Blood; but being opened where it was dilated, it threw forth more Blood than the whole capacity of the skin of the thigh and leg ſhould contain: Therefore, ſay I, as the Blood from the Heart is ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad by the Arteries, ſo being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by the branches of the Veins into the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> 'tis again ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into the Ventricles of the Heart it ſelf.</p>
                        <p>But leſt any ſhould doubt that the Blood which ſpringeth out of the Veins hath not flowed into them from their Fellow-Arteries, I opened the Crural vein where it moſt appeared; the Blood ſwiftly ſprung from it: then I tyed it's Fellow-Artery, and which is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful! the force being abated, the Blood of the Vein diſtilled by drops firſt, and at laſt quire ſtopped: But the freedome of the looſed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery renewed its ſtream; and the Blood iſſuing out of the Vein with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170048:30"/>former vigour ſhew what commerce the Arteries have with the Veins.</p>
                        <p>Neither [Reader] let it trouble thee, that ſometimes, though ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Blood ſpringeth from the Vein on this ſide the bandage where the Veins are then moſt fallen. Believe me, not affirming but as one that hath tryed, that the diſperſed twigs do disburthen themſelves of this Blood ſo diſcharged into the <hi>Vena cava.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>One day (as I have ſaid) I was at work, and wounded on both ſides the Ligature of the tyed Vein, behold not onely beyond, but on this ſide the Ligature I wondred to ſee unceaſable ſpringing of the Blood. I then did ſeparate the <hi>Vena cava</hi> from her coverings upwards, even to the diviſion of the Iliack Branches, and I bound all the Branches of the Veins I met with in my paſſage ſtraitly, the Blood ſtopp'd: Then indeed on this ſide the Ligature the Blood evaniſh'd, and was exhauſt from that place up to the Valve that lurketh in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170048:31"/>the Groin, its Clack ſtopping al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together the deſcent of the Blood which preſſed it, ſhew clearly that the Blood had no power to deſcend by the Veins.</p>
                        <p>Then concluded I, If the Blood be onely ſpread by the Arteries, a member, the Artery being tyed, may be amputed without blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Sooner then I had ſaid it I tyed the Crural Artery, leaving the Veins looſe, and at the ham a little below the bandage I cut off his leg: ſome drops of Blood in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed did flow from it, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as the laſt Valves of the cut-aſunder Veins did not contain, and with which the twigs of the Arteries diſperſed up and down the skin for the nouriſhment thereof were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. But when the Cut-veins are emptied of that Blood which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the Valves, and the ſmall Branches of the Cutaneous Arteries are ſtopp'd, partly by the congeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing occurſe of Cold repreſſing the Heat, partly by the contraction of the grieved parts through the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170048:31"/>wound, the flowing of the Blood did altogether ceaſe; neither did any more Blood ſpring from any of the diſperſed Veſſels ſpread over the whole amputation, till way was made for the Arterial Blood by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying the Crural Artery.</p>
                        <p>I tried the ſame in the Axillar, in the Jugular: but becauſe 'tis more troubleſome in a Dog by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his ſhort neck, in a Gooſe the Experiment did eaſily ſucced.</p>
                        <p>And leſt you ſhould deny that in a man which is demonſtrable in a brute, pray you look upon your Arm, if leanneſs perchance ſuffer the full Veins to appear; there if you rub downward with your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, it then ſwelleth moſt, you will wonder to ſee the knotting of the Shut-Valves, and from them down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the preſſure of the finger the Canal of the Vein empty. Look to a Chirurgion ebrathing a Vein, he binding ſtraitly a Ligature about the brawn of the Arm, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the flowing of the Blood from the hand to the heart: He looſeth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170048:32"/>a little the Blood-band, being to hard tyed, that the Artery being freed from the ſtraitneſs of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Muſcle of the Arm may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh the choked Veins with a freſh ſtream of Blood.</p>
                        <p>Neither imagine thou that I have but once made Trial of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of the Blood in the greater Veſſels of the Veins and Arteries. Indeed having tried this every where, yea in the ſmalleſt Branches of both, as my ſight would ſerve, I found it every where the ſame. This was ſhewn by Ligatures in the hands and feet: This both the breathing and Valves of each Vein, yea thoſe in the finger, did demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170048:32"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The <hi>Vena porta</hi> doth diſcharge it ſelf by the Liver into the <hi>Vena cava</hi> of the Blood it receives from the Coeliack Artery; and hence the Gallant <hi>Harvey</hi>'s Opinion is confirm'd.</head>
                        <p>HAving manifeſted the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of the Blood from the Heart by the Arteries unto the Extremities of the body, and from thence by the Veins hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again, I reſolved to know how this holds in the <hi>Vena prrta.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Having tyed the Branches of the Coeliack Arteries, where the Blood enters the Meſentery, they fell and roſe after no different manner from the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> ſwelling from the Trunk to the bandage, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming flaccid betwixt the Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Inteſtines.</p>
                        <p>I oft-times tyed the Meſeraick-port-veins, yet nevertheleſs they filled betwixt the Inteſtines and Ligatures, and did altogether fall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170048:33"/>betwixt the Ligature and Liver; yea being opened on both ſides the Ligature, the Blood iſſued out. I tried the Veins of the Spleen with the ſame ſucceſs; alſo that Vein which is called <hi>Vas breve,</hi> betwixt the Stomack and Ligature in the middle thereof full; but betwixt it and the Spleen it ſeemed to wain, notwithſtanding being opened on both ſides, the Blood followed.</p>
                        <p>From theſe I inferr [except you pleaſe to admit frequent Synana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomoſies betwixt the Branches of the Port-vein and their Fellow-Arteries] that the Blood is either ſtopp'd by none, or at leaſt very ſmall Valves within the Branches of that Vein.</p>
                        <p>The opinion of <hi>Riolan</hi> preſently came into my mind, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Blood of the Vein-port doth not at all paſs into the <hi>Vena cava.</hi> And the Authority of ſo famous a man had altogether ſtopp'd my fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſearch, if my eyes, which I appointed ſtrict Judges of the game, had not withſtood it, reproaching
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170048:33"/>my lazineſs that fail'd in the midſt of the courſe.</p>
                        <p>Therefore being more troubled, I had my recourſe to the Trunk of the <hi>Vena porta,</hi> and I bound with a Ligature the Meſenterick branch three fingers broad from the Liver: At the ſame diſtance I bound the Splenetick; the knot indeed was ſtrait, but eaſy to be looſed. Scarce had I left off binding, when behold the Pipe betwixt the Ligature and Liver which before roſe Turgid, was now a bloodleſs Chanel, and became flaccid, on the other ſide the Pipes of both the Branches were filled with an indifferent ſtream of Blood flowing from the Inteſtins and Meſentery, yea from the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack and Spleen alſo.</p>
                        <p>I fill'd again the emptied trunk of the <hi>Vena porta,</hi> by untying one of the Ligatures; which being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently again tyed, next the Liver, it was emptied. The Experiment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing frequently reiterated, it was evident that the Blood flow'd abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly and ſwiftly out of the <hi>Vena
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170048:34"/>porta</hi> into the Windings of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And perceiving that through the Concavity of the Liver the <hi>Vena porta</hi> did divide it ſelf in many Branchings for the conveyance of Blood after the manner of Arteries: Whether [ſay I] doth not the <hi>Vena porta</hi> it ſelf, inſtead of an Artery, thruſt out into the Liver, an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of fervid Blood for the che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of the ſtomack and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocting faculty? The ſmalneſs of the Coeliack Branches being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as I thought, unable for ſo great an effect.</p>
                        <p>And rightly I thought it; for the <hi>Vena porta</hi> within the Liver is altogether an Artery: For as the Arteries iſſue their Blood from out their Trunk into their Branches, but the Veins return it from their Branches into the Trunk: So the <hi>Vena porta</hi> from its Trunk diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteth Blood to its furtheſt Branches that are within the Liver, which Blood it hath gathered into its Trunk from the Branches it hath without the Concavity of the ſame.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170048:34"/>And as the Coats of the Arteries are thicker than thoſe of the Veins, ſo the <hi>Vena porta</hi> hath a thicker skin within the Liver than it hath in its Veſſels without the ſame.</p>
                        <p>Neither believe that I depart from ocular inſpection when I ſay that the Coat of the <hi>Vena porta</hi> is thicker within the Liver; for I broke in pieces at leiſure all the ſubſtance of the Liver of the Beaſt which I anatomiz'd, and laid open the form of the uncloath'd <hi>Vena porta:</hi> The Tunicle whereof with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Liver retain'd the thinneſs of a Vein, but within the Liver did altogether appear to be an Artery: So that it did undoubtedly appear which before I did ſuſpect, That ſome of the Veſſels of the Blood, as the <hi>Aorta,</hi> deſerve onely the name of Arteries; Others admit onely the name of Veins, as the <hi>Vena cava;</hi> And to conclude, ſome are appointed by Nature for both du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſuch as we have found the <hi>Vena porta</hi> to be.</p>
                        <p>But when I doubted whither ſo
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170048:35"/>great a current of Blood flowed, and believing it had its courſe unto the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> I tyed [I will not ſay with the Antients the Trunk, but] the branch thereof where it entreth the gibboſity of the Liver, as far from the Liver as I could; and then the Blood ruſhing to the bandage [the branch greatly riſing betwixt the Ligature and Liver] ſhewed the manifeſt commerce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Vena porta</hi> and the <hi>Vena cava;</hi> and how appoſitly the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edſt Engliſh Phyſician, <hi>Will: Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey,</hi> held the motion of the whole Blood to be Circular.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170048:35"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That the Blood floweth out of the Right Ventricle of the Heart through the Lungs into the Left Ventricle.</head>
                        <p>THis one thing did remain to perfect ſo great a Circulation, to know fully the Paſſage of the Blood from the Veins through the Heart into the Arteries. The evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent diverſity of Cavities and Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for the carrying of the Blood both in Children in the womb, and more adult perſons, did vex my troubled mind.</p>
                        <p>Indeed in perſons of firm age that oval perforation, or rather communication [which is ſprinkled with <hi>Botalus</hi> the Inventor's name] or, if you will, that Synanaſtomoſis uſeth not to remain. It is that by which, in the Child in the womb, the Blood directly from the <hi>Vena cava</hi> filleth the right Ventricle of the Heart; alſo by the Venal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery entreth immediately the left Ventricle.</p>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170048:36"/>
                        <p>Neither doth that little Ductus remain Pervious, but degenerateth into a Ligament, by which the <hi>Aorta</hi> of the Child in the womb receiveth the Blood through the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial vein, the ſhorteſt way from the right Ventricle, without any turning into the left.</p>
                        <p>Then at laſt, that the commerce of the Heart, with the Entrances of the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> might be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, with the famouſeſt Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts I conſidered the ſtructure of the ſubſtance of this Noble-intrail; and in the firſt place, the three doors of the three-corner'd Valves, ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate betwixt the joyning of the <hi>Vena cava</hi> to the right Ventricle of the Heart, offered themſelves to view: I was willing to take notice of their office, which was, to give eaſy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to the Blood into the Heart, but ſtopt its return into the <hi>Vena cava.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The impervious ſolidity of the Septi, or Partition of the Heart which lyeth betwixt the Ventricles, denied it altogether a paſſage.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170048:36"/>Therefore I inferr'd, the Blood iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth out of the right Ventricle into the Arterial vein: And indeed in that place the three Sigmatoidal or S-like Valves give place to it ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forwards, but withſtand its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
                        <p>Nevertheleſs having burſt aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the partition, I viewed the left Ventricle: It differed from the right in that it was of a more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long and narrower hollowneſs: Into two Entrances of it two Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales were inſerted, on this ſide that which they name the <hi>Arteria Venoſa,</hi> on the other ſide the <hi>Aorta</hi> was placed, at the boundings of both were placed Valves: This [the <hi>Aorta</hi> or great Artery] had, as in the <hi>Arteria Venoſa,</hi> three ſigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toidal Valves, to give way to the Blood thruſt out, and to ſtop its return: That [the <hi>Arteria Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſa</hi>] had two Miter-like Valves, that kept Centry, to give Entrance to the Blood into the Heart, and to ſtop its flight from thence.</p>
                        <p>By reaſon of this fabrick and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170048:37"/>of the Heart, and the offices of its Inſtruments, I could not any more approve their denying the flowing of the Blood from the Heart into the Lungs by the Arterial Vein, and again its return from the Lungs into the Heart by the Venal Artery.</p>
                        <p>And leſt ſome perverſe people ſhould charge me onely with ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, behold I produce an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment. I bound with a Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture both the Veſſels as near the Lungs as was poſſible, and then the Arterial Vein in its body was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated betwixt the Heart and Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, beyond the ſame Ligature to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards its furtheſt Branches in the Lungs it became flaccid: But the Ductreſſes of the Venal Artery al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in a contrary effect did ſwell and fall.</p>
                        <p>But ſeeing indeed our ſpeech is fallen on the two Veins of the Lungs, the Anatomiſts have with unfit tearms [in my judgement] na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them: For what mattereth it, if with the ſubtil <hi>des Cartes,</hi> I call
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170048:37"/>that onely an Artery through which the right Ventricle disburthens it ſelf into the Lungs; ſeeing both the thickneſs of its Coat, the figure of its Valves, and the office of its Pipe receiving Blood from the Heart, do altogether aſſimulate it to the reſt of the bodies of Arteries? And why, I pray you, entitle they that an Arterial Vein through which the Lungs diſgorge their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtreams into the Heart, ſeeing the teſtimony of its Coats, Valves and Office, aſſert it a Vein? Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding name them as they will, 'tis all one to me, ſo they be known: But a demonſtrative truth in this matter ſhould not have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed it ſelf to <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his opinion.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170048:38"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The Circulation of the Blood in the Child in the Womb.</head>
                        <p>THat which we have already ſhewn concerning the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of the Blood, I would have thee [Reader] to underſtand it chiefly of grown perſons: Not to deny its Circulation in Children in the womb, but that in them the Circular motion differeth a little in its paſſages.</p>
                        <p>By the Hypogaſtrick Arteries the Blood is carried into the womb of the Woman with Child; the Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilical Vein carrieth that part of it which is beſt concoct into the Liver of the Embryon: but that which is more ſerous and unconcoct return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by the Maternal Veins unto the Heart as its Pot, whilſt the thicker groweth together into the <hi>Placenta</hi> or Lump, as into the wombs Liver.</p>
                        <p>The <hi>Vena cava</hi> thruſteth the Blood, receiv'd into the Embryons
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170048:38"/>Liver, from thence into the right Ventricle of the Heart, where it joyns with it, and ſo into the left Ventricle thereof, by the then open Oval-paſſages. The Blood going out of the right Ventricle into the Arterial Vein, partly by an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected little Pipe, as it were by a ſloping Canale, it floweth freely into the <hi>Aorta;</hi> Partly a good quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity poſſeſſing the Lungs, oppreſſeth them with ſo great weight, in reſpect of want of breathing for the hard paſſage from the furtheſt branches of the Arterial Vein into the Venal Artery, that the Lungs of the Child in the womb [if it did not breath ſometimes] repreſenting both the colour and denſity of the Liver, would never ſwim above water.</p>
                        <p>Certes, Reſpiration ſtirreth up the Blood in the Venal Artery. The <hi>Bronchia</hi> [Canales of the Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe] by their breathing dilatation preſſing together their fellows, on the one part the Arterial Vein, and on the other part the Venal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, to preſs out the contained
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170048:39"/>Blood ſo far as the Valves will ſuffer.</p>
                        <p>The Blood of the left Ventricle immediately penetrateth into the <hi>Aorta,</hi> and from thence ruſhing to the furtheſt parts of the body, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth by the Veins to the Heart, as hath been ſhewn in Adult per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
                        <p>And becauſe the Umbilick Vein emitteth more Blood than the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of the Child requireth, the Providence of Nature hath branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out a pair of Branches, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts of the Umbilick Vein, either of them from the Iliack, or [which I have moſt frequently obſerv'd] from the Hypogaſtriack Arteries even unto the <hi>Placenta.</hi> They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the Blood that is more than nouriſheth the Child into the Liver of the womb, whether this be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd by the celerity of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or whether the impure maſs of the Mothers blood requires a better digeſtion by the mixture of a warmer.</p>
                        <p>But leſt I ſhould ſeem to have
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170048:39"/>found out this reflux by vain Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, put I pray thee a ſtraw into the Umbilick Veſſels that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the <hi>Placenta</hi> or Lump; then blow thou, and the Vein alone will carry the wind into the Child: But on the contrary, if thou blow by the Reed into the Child, the Arteries will carry the wind into the Lump, the Veins remaining al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together flaccid.</p>
                        <p>At laſt the Umbilical Vein by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees becoming unprofitable, dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerateth into a Ligament: by the ſame chance the Canale of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Vein, going into the <hi>Aorta,</hi> evaniſheth, and the Botalian per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foration is filled: but the Umbilick Arteries nevertheleſs remain. I have many times obſerv'd it in cutting up of Adult perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> the wind blown into the Hypograſtriack and Iliack Arteries, did not onely ſhew the Umbilicals near the Navil by the ſmall tumor it did raiſe, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring their infinite Branches on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſide, by them its empty tumor
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170048:40"/>declar'd the many branchings of the Artery in that place.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="chapter">
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That the Arterious Blood is partly by Synanaſtomoſies poured out of the Arteries into the Veins; partly being extravaſated by the Anaſtomoſies of the Arteries, returneth again into the Veins.</head>
                        <p>HAving demonſtrated the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of the Blood to and out of the Heart, 'tis fitting that according to the example of thoſe that are well deſervers of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomick Commonwealth, we ſearch out, with an inqueſt reſembling the former, its paſſages from the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries into the Veins.</p>
                        <p>Many are of opinion that the furtheſt points of the Arteries are inſerted into as ſmall parts of the Veins; but the ſmalneſs of the points of the minute Veſſels not to be diſcerned by any eyes, though
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170048:40"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170048:41"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170048:41"/>arm'd with Spectacles doth not confirm, doth not confute this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
                        <p>They aver alſo, that wind blown into the roots of the <hi>Vena porta</hi> within the Liver, doth enter the conjoyn'd Branches of the <hi>Vena cava;</hi> and that it doth inſinuate it ſelf from the Trunk of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Vein into the Lungs, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt Branches of the Venal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</p>
                        <p>I have many times tryed it in the Liver, but the Experiment ever failed; I doubt whether more by defect of breath in me, or errour in them. In the Lungs indeed I have found that the common paſſage of the Synanaſtomoſies of the ſame Pipes were open.</p>
                        <p>One day it was my buſineſs to view the Arterial Vein, being made bare of all its Cloathing. I did obſerve it, not with a few knots of Embracements to ſtick faſt to the Venal Artery. Putting a Reed into it in that place where 'tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert into the Heart, I blew; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170048:42"/>the ſpreading breath did raiſe the bloodleſs Canals, and being roll'd to the ends of the Capillar Veins, was received into the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowneſs of the Venal Artery, which is indeed an evident token of their Synanaſtomoſie. But though it held in the Lungs, yet nevertheleſs I will not conclude it holds ſo in the Liver or Muſcles.</p>
                        <p>Indeed I will confeſs, that by the intermediate openings of the Synanaſtomoſies, that the Blood may be turned out of one Veſſel into another, ſeeing the individible coherence of the Veins with the Arteries in ſome places, proves this, and their not eaſy ſeparation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tearing of both. But I believe he admitteth abſurdly this Synana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomoſis where the Veins have no coherence with the Arteries; yea rather I would believe, that a part of the Blood by the Anaſtomoſies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the incloſures of the Arteries, doth abound to be ſtrain'd in the fleſh, that that of it which is more exactly concoct may turn to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170048:42"/>in the ſimular parts, But that which is not well digeſted, may return into the Veins, which perchance in all places without have entrances to their moſt inward places.</p>
                        <p>For if the perpetual Flux of the Blood within the Veſſels caſteth forth no Blood without the Veſſels, whence proceeds the increaſe of the bodies bulk? And if the ſubſtance of the parts of the body be in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual motion, from whence, I pray you, will proceed the reſtorement of the tabid leanneſs of withered bodies?</p>
                        <p>There is indeed ſome ſeedy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the Blood fit for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of the decayings of the parts, <hi>viz.</hi> That which being more concoct uſeth to unite it ſelf into a fibrous thickneſs: And indeed, the Blood drawn from the Limbs into hot water, doth ſpread its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity and colour in the water, when in the bottome of the baſon there remaineth a fleſhy thickneſs of membranous dregs compos'd of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170048:43"/>white fibers, and therefore more fit for the ſolidity of the body; to wit, that which either remained af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſatisfying of the parts, or was melted by the waſhing vigour, may be, of the following Blood, or was tranſvaſated by the ſhort paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the Synanaſtomoſies, and did haſten to be recocted in the Pot of the Heart.</p>
                        <p>And leſt any ſhould confound the Offices of Synanaſtomoſies and Anaſtomoſies by reaſon of the likeneſs of the words, I call Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtomoſies the intermediate open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Arteries cohering to Veins for the carrying of the Blood out of one Veſſel into another; I call Anaſtomoſies the furtheſt points of the Arteries whereby the Blood is extravaſated and received by the tunnels of the Veins for the gathering together of the ſame.</p>
                        <div type="section">
                           <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170048:43"/>
                           <head>The OBJECTIONS againſt the Extravaſation of the Blood, anſwered.</head>
                           <p>BUT I hear them objecting the prerogative of the more ſubtil Blood in the Artery: For if the Blood be ſtrain'd in the fleſh, how comes it to paſs that the Veins iſſue forth more groſs Blood?</p>
                           <p>Deſervedly indeed, and together with thee wondring would I be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd at the undeſerved groſneſs of the Blood, if the Arteries ſhould thruſt into the Veins all the ſeroſity they contain; if the heat with the ſame warmneſs; if their Blood un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt with the age of the withering fleſh: But no man doubts but that the ſeroſity of the Arteries partly goes a part into the Reins, partly is ſpread in the fleſh, and partly evaniſheth by inſenſible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration; even as by the thickneſs of the Coats of the Arteries, and neighbourhood of the Fountain, the heat is ſuſtain'd: So by the coldneſs
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170048:44"/>of the Spermatick part, and by the diſtance of the forſaken heart it doth by little and little grow chiller: Adde the eaſy paſſages of the pores for its expiration: For as the fleſh increaſeth by food, ſo they periſh by faſting: This is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by the interchange of vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs and languiſhing each day, yea by hunger and fulneſs. That which now doth grow into fleſh, within a ſhort time withering, doth for the moſt part give place to the ſucceeding nouriſhment, <hi>viz.</hi> that which did grow together by the offence of cold, being melted by the coming of a hot ſtream again, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neweth the journey it was ſtopt in, and doth return to be recocted in its former forge.</p>
                           <p>The ſeroſity is diminiſhed, the heat tempered, the dregs of the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged fleſh mixed with it: What won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then that the Arterial Blood is excelled by the Venous, in reſpect of the conſiſtency of its ſubſtance?</p>
                           <p>Neither canſt thou more wiſely object the unavoydable corruption
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170048:44"/>of its ſtanding without the Veſſels. Indeed the wandring Blood, out of the incloſures of the Arteries, doth abound through the whole bulk of the body; the increaſe of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creature declareth this; the ſcarlet dye of the bluſhing brow holdeth this forth; the red incir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culing burning tumors do the like; and ſuch kind of paſſions evaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in paleneſs immediatly after Blood-letting.</p>
                           <p>But notwithſtanding, the onely narrowneſs of the Veins ſtayeth the Blood, if by the again flowing of it they be ſtrain'd beyond the bounds of their capaciouſneſs; and in its ſtay, if it be longer, that Blood which followeth is defiled by the mixture of the retain'd dregs, and doth end in divers ſickneſſes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of hurtful humours. So while the heat doth burn more vehemently, the Blood is kindled into an inflamation, Thou ſhalt behold the more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful ſeroſity, except exhauſted in ſweat, or exhaled by tranſpiration,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170048:45"/>grow into a Dropſy, or ſometimes ſpread it ſelf into a Rheumatiſm; the Flegm endeth in an Oedema; the Choler boyleth into an Eryſipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, and Melancholy is condens'd into a Schirrus.</p>
                           <p>Hence 'tis that the Blood it ſelf doth grow into a Pluriſy, <hi>viz.</hi> when ſudden cold ſeizeth on the inward parts, it beateth back moſt unſeaſonably the more vehement heat of breathing; and with its ſudden cold binding up the Canals of the intercoſtial Veins, it ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Chanels, now ſcarce ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for the reflowing Blood, which by the more frequent motion of the Syſtoles is gathered thither, and turneth into atter the ſame Blood, being longer ſeated there, and extravaſated, wandreth in the fleſh, except it be prevented by Phlebotomy.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170048:45"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The beginning of the Blood's mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is inquir'd after; the innate weight of the Blood, though the Arteries ſhould pay the part of a Syphon with the Veins, is ſhewn not to be enough for its Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
                        <p>THE undiſcovered cauſe of the diſcovered matter rather ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated than abated my grief: The motion of the Blood is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, but its beginning being yet conceal'd, challengeth me to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> new labour, the difficulties of which, (Reader) I will eſſay to make plain by theſe admonitions.</p>
                        <p>The Blood ruſheth forward ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by its own proper incitement, or 'tis thruſt forward by anothers; we acknowledge it hath no proper one, except its heavineſs, whoſe vertue I will prove vaniſhing by theſe following reaſons.</p>
                        <p>The Blood indeed, whom the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate weight may carry downward
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170048:46"/>by the deſcendent Arteries, and the Trunk aſcendent of the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> cannot by the ſelf-ſame endeavour flow to the upper parts of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent Arteries, neither by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent ſtem of the <hi>Vena cava;</hi> except, with ſome famous Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, you aſcribe the reaſon of this effect to the diſpoſition of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels: <hi>For</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the Arteries ſo cohere with the Veins, that you may ſay not undeſervedly their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick imitateth a Syphon.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>They call a Syphon a reflex'd Pipe, either whoſe declining Legs uphold a high Angle, or whoſe elevat Legs lean on a depreſſed Angle.</p>
                        <p>That therefore the aſcending li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor may come to the high Angle of the Syphon, 'tis needful that the Leg by which it ſhould flow, be plac'd under a more depreſs out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſending Veſſel, that from thence the greater weight of the liquid heap may make the weaker water mova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to follow it through the other door. So by the aſcending ſtem of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170048:46"/>the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> which the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Nature hath plac'd a little lower than the Entrances of the aſcending Arteries, the Blood flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down (ſay they) which for this ought altogether following to aſcend.</p>
                        <p>And as the Liquor, ruſhing by its own weight into the depreſſed Angle of the other Syphon, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected out of the bottome by its own inſtinct, till on both ſides, by an equal Superficies it point forth the quietneſs of a juſt ballance; and if the Pipe of reflection being more ſhort, doth hold abroad a more declin'd openneſs than the tunnel of the other Leg, it cometh to paſs that for the ſame heavineſs, that 'tis poured out by its own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſtream. So the Blood [ſay they] by the ear'd trunk of the deſcending <hi>Aorta</hi> throwing it ſelf headlong to the lower parts, of its own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord riſeth up again from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome by the deſcendent <hi>Vena cava,</hi> and by the door of the ſame, which is a little low ſituate, by a ſponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170048:47"/>flowing again is refunded into the pool of the Heart. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, Reader, leſt the doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the name ſhould trouble thee, that that is call'd the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Vena cava</hi> which ſpringeth upward from the Heart; but that which ſpreadeth Branches from this down to the extremities of the parts, is call'd the Deſcendent, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the name from its Original, not from its office.</p>
                        <p>Truly you may ſay, that with the workmanſhip of Nature, Truth it ſelf hath conſpir'd to their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and that injuriouſly I deny my aſſent to moſt evident rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
                        <p>But if with me you take notice, that at the ſame time the liquor aſcendeth to the high Angle of the Syphon, that it ruſheth downward; and again, that it aſcendeth in the ſame moment from the depreſs'd Angle of the overturned Syphon, by which it is poured into it: Then it will be clear, how incongruous the ſucceſſion of continual flowing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170048:47"/>of the Syphon is with the motion of the Blood.</p>
                        <p>And indeed the Blood, while the Expreſſion of the Syſtoles thruſteth it in the wide-open Arteries, at the ſame moment by their Extremities, penetrateth into the Veins: But then onely it breaketh out of the Veins into the Heart, when the Syſtole ceaſing, leaveth to the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtole its own part by intercourſe to be acted. And even from this 'tis clear, that the Blood no waies imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth the liquor in a Syphon.</p>
                        <p>But becauſe we do hardly depart from thoſe things that pleaſe us, I demand, that if the Chanels of Blood play the part of a Syphon, and for that the Law of Conter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure requireth an equal fulneſs neceſſarily on both ſides, how comes it to paſs, that in a dead Body Death doth altogether empty the Arteries, whilſt the Veins remain turgid?</p>
                        <p>Yea the Experiments of Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation will voyce againſt the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon. The Jugular Vein repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the emiſſary of a ſtanding Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170048:48"/>from its ſublime Angle into the Heart: When I had tyed this Vein in the Neck, notwithſtanding, by the Aſcendent Arteries Blood was ſent upwards, yea and above the Ligature it extended above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Jugular Vein.</p>
                        <p>The ſtraitned Pipe of the Crural Vein taught the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming flaccid from the Ligature towards the Heart, cleared that it iſſued the Blood thitherward: But ſhall I believe that any fooliſhly will attribute the aſcent of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Heart unto the heavineſs of the ruſhing heaps of Blood into the <hi>Aorta?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But neither that Artery it ſelf which watereth the Leg when 'tis tyed [if it be to be attributed to the weight of the Blood, as the motion in an inverſe Syphon] can be eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate under the Ligature, againſt Experience; For the ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains of Blood there, will not be able to thruſt upwards the whole weight of Blood which weighteth in the <hi>Vena cava.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170048:48"/>
                        <p>But when I ſaid, the exhauſt Arteries of dead Bodies, do not thou believe 'tis to be attributed unto the evaniſhing ſubtilty of Arterial Blood. For this alſo hath its own denſity, neither leſs perchance than that groſsneſs which is included not onely in the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> but <hi>Porta</hi> alſo.</p>
                        <p>Eaſy experience will ſupply my admonition. The wounds of a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Beaſt at the ſame time empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Vena cava,</hi> together with the <hi>Aorta,</hi> and, if thou pleaſe, the <hi>Vena porta</hi> it ſelf: Let the Blood drawn out of each place ſettle in its own platter; Let none of them be diſſolv'd into a vapor, and except that which was drawn from the Branches of the Arteries bluſhed with a more clear purple, with a moyſt vain trial ſhouldſt thou ſearch after a difference.</p>
                        <p>Thou mayſt in a dying Creature ſtop the Arterial Blood, if thou tye the Artery in the Leg; and I my ſelf many times having tried this, I beheld the Artery towards the Heart to be
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170048:49"/>tumid, with Blood that did not at all evaniſh.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, ſeeing neither the courſe of a Syphon agreeth to the Circular motion of the Blood, neither the weight thereof ſeems to ſerve for that purpoſe, yea many times 'tis impediment thereto, as 'tis clear in Limbs hanging more negligently, Lazineſs making the vigour of the Blood more ſtupid; we are to have our recourſe to the vertue of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal incitement, the innate one failing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170048:49"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The impulſe of the Syſtole alone is not enough for the Circular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Blood. In a Diaſtole there is no Attraction.</head>
                        <p>THE impulſion of a Syſtole, Attraction of a Diaſtole, the rough contraction of the Veſſels, and endeavour of the adjacent parts upon every occaſion, ſeem all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecally to affect the Blood. Let us diſcover by an exact Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which of theſe, and how much each of them conferreth to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Blood.</p>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Of the Impulſe of the Syſtole.</head>
                           <p>The Syſtole thruſteth the Blood; &amp; that part of it ſo promoted driveth before it the former part; but that which laſt leaves the Heart, whilſt the Arteries are emptying in dying Creatures, albeit no following part doth drive it, nevertheleſs haſtneth into the Veins; And while we tye
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170048:50"/>the Crural Artery in a living Beaſt, beyond the Ligature we ſee it to iſſue out that Blood which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd towards the Extremities, becoming by little and little flaccid, without incitement of Blood fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which is ſtopt by the thread.</p>
                           <p>Let us try the ſame in the Vein which watereth the Leg, by ſtaying the continued flowing of the Blood with a Ligature; then ſwelling from the Thread towards the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme parts, the Blood nevertheleſs haſting towards the Heart, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate that the courſe of the Blood by the Arteries towards the Extremities, is not to be attributed alone to the impulſe of the Syſtole urgent, neither its return thence by the Veins to the Heart.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Of the Diaſtole's Attraction.</head>
                           <p>We are therefore to obſerve the office of the Diaſtole. 'Tis the duty of it to receive the Blood: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as ſome think, it draweth it
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170048:50"/>by <hi>Attraction,</hi> or ſuch it, and ſo aſſiſteth the impulſe of the Syſtole, is to be enquir'd after.</p>
                           <p>Diaſtole immediately followeth the Syſtole: Therefore when the Syſtole endeth, the Canals of the urging Veins ſwelling, the heap of the Blood prepared for eruption beateth at the gates of the Heart, and doth ingurgitate its Ventricles, the Diaſtole onely offering the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of obedience; ſo that it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly appeareth how ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous it is to appoint an <hi>Attractive,</hi> or rather, if you will; a <hi>ſucking</hi> vertue, which in the buſineſs of fluid things I ever tolerated with tingling ears.</p>
                           <p>And indeed, whatſoever our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries argue, and whatſoever En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins they apply in aſſiſtance of <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction,</hi> Experience, which is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more eloquent, doth both throw it down and refute it. It pleaſeth me to fight with the fame Engins, that being vanquiſh'd by their own Arms, at laſt they may confeſs thoſe examples they bring, of the Air in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170048:51"/>the Bellows; of the water in the Aeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipilaes, or Pump, or Reed; And to conclude, of the Fleſh in Cupping Glaſſes, ſucceeds by no allurement of ſuccing, but onely by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of <hi>External Impulſion.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>That I may be more able with a more happy ſucceſs to unfold this hitherto unfolded Myſterie, 'tis to be ſuppos'd that the Globe of Earth and Water is compreſs'd, not onely by the weight of the Air, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the vertue of Elateries in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in it: But becauſe indeed that is not eaſily ſuppos'd which yet is in doubt, ſuffer thy ſelf, I pray thee, Reader, to be perſwaded with me by the ſame Arguments, and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Experiments.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170048:51"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> 'Tis ſhewn by Experiments, that there is not onely a Weight in the Air, but likewiſe a rarefactive Elatery.</head>
                        <p>I would treat of the Air's pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deroſity, yea in its proper (as they ſay) place, except it were an Argument known to all. For who doth not ſee the Air of its own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to deſcend into the Chinks and Ditches, yea even into the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Center of the Earth, if you delve ſo deep? Who doth not know that a little Bladder, the more tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid it is, is ſo much more heavy than it ſelf being flaccid? Who, if he weigh a Gun burthened with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſed Air [they call it a Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun] will not obſerve that its weight then is heavier than 'tis when it is diſcharged? To conclude, to whom is it unknown that the lightneſs of an Aeolipila, the Air of which is rarified exactly by the force of heat, is not at all to be compared with
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170048:52"/>the heavineſs of it being cold?</p>
                        <p>Neither indeed believe thou that I am affrighted with the opinion of that kind of airy weight in refund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vapours of the Athmoſphere. For by the Air I underſtand the Athmoſphere, neither for the preſent doth my Philoſophy aſcend higher.</p>
                        <p>Feign to thy ſelf this, as a heap of ſpongious, or rather woolly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter encompaſſing the Earth-watriſh Globe, whoſe ſuperiour parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are ſuſteined by the inferiour, compreſſing it by degrees, ſo that the nearer they come to the Earth, ſo much the more they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed compactly by the weight of the parts incumbent; And for that cauſe by its Spontaneous dilatation [which I call Elater] howſoever the heap'd on burthen do preſs them down, yet the under parts, if they have liberty, will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to rarifie themſelves.</p>
                        <p>Hence I inferr, that the loweſt of thoſe parts, as being plac'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the whole burthen, ſo to be moſt condenſed of them all; And
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170048:52"/>for this reaſon the ſuperfice of the Earth-watriſh Orb is preſſed of the ſame, not by its weight alone, but alſo by the vertue of his Elatery, whoſe endeavour to rarifie is moſt valid.</p>
                        <p>But becauſe they are words, and I have given you leave to proceed from the Ears to the Eyes, I will prevent thy deſire, and I will view the miſty ſecrets of the Air by the ſearch of Experience, which I at all times follow as my Leader.</p>
                        <p>I will produce in the firſt place ſome Experiments concerning <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuum,</hi> or Emptineſs, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as yet have not been commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Preſs; no Monuments of my own deep cunning, far be it from me to arrogate to my ſelf the glory of thoſe detected Miracles which were not firſt diſcovered to me: For whatſoever I did exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitly elaborate with an exact en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour more frequently about ſo weighty a matter for fear of errour
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170048:53"/>which troubled me, it was imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not invention.</p>
                        <p>I will produce Authors, not of Books, which as yet I have not ſo much as heard to be extant; but of thoſe Experiments at leaſt which follow, and whoſe Authority is great, and Name venerable.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="experiments">
                        <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170048:53"/>
                        <head>Experiments PHYSICO-MATHEMATICAL OF VACUITY.</head>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>The firſt Experiment.</hi> A little Bladder being emptied of its own accord at falling down of Quick-ſilver, rarifying in the high Viol of the Pipe, declareth the Rarefactive Elatery of the Air.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>
                                 <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Obervallius,</hi> the moſt famous Reader of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicks</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> in the Kings Chair, did after this manner ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, while I was preſent, in favour of that vertue whereby the Air of it ſelf doth dilate it ſelf, indeed not without ſucceſs.</p>
                           <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170048:54"/>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>assorted vials</figDesc>
                              <p>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>A</item>
                                    <item>B</item>
                                    <item>C</item>
                                    <item>D</item>
                                 </list>
                              </p>
                           </figure>
                           <p>A wonderful ſight appeared to the beholders; the Carp's little Bladder, which the ſtraitneſs of the narrowneck kept up into the higher bottle, did of its own accord ſwell again. Indeed I had been amazed [except my mind had cur'd the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of mine eyes] at the ſwelling fulneſs of that ſudden Meteor in C, in the middle [as they ſay] of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity. But the reſidue of the Air within the ſecret paſſages of the writhed indeed, but not altogether exhauſted Bladder, taught that there was a Spontaneous Elatery in the Air, whilſt free, and not compreſſed by the weight of any thing lying above it.</p>
                           <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170048:55"/>
                           <p>For 'tis but a vain reaſon they bring; <hi>The Airs ſubtility,</hi> ſay they, <hi>penetrateth the thickneſs of the glaſs, and being ſpread abroad in every place of the writhed bladder, at laſt entreth the ſame by its pores, and extends the whole to his former ſwelling.</hi> But let them remember that which they believe, That the Glaſs is on every ſide pervious to the entring Air, and therefore the Air is carried in all places with the ſame force of its ruſhing rayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Bladder, ſtaying in the middle of the Bottle C; ſo that it ſhould rather compreſs and oppreſs it, than re-acting it ſelf againſt it ſelf, have a care to raiſe its unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable dilation. Adde this, that the peirc'd on all hands B adder could not ſtay the Air, or contain it which it had received within.</p>
                           <p>Neither troubles it me, that they ſay that the pores pervious open to the entring Air, forbid its return. For then the entred Air ſhould be compell'd, by the Valves ſhut on all ſides, to remain within; So that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170048:56"/>the little Bladder ſhould retain, the ſwelling it hath once receiv'd, and ſhould ſtill remain full; which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to be moſt falſe, by the lankneſs of the Bladder, either by inclining the engin a little, or by admitting therein a little portion of the Air from abroad. And hence their opinion is ruined, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Bladder ſwelleth again by the Spirits of the Quick-ſilver.</p>
                           <p>By which, ſeeing it clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the Air which after writhing lay faſt in the moſt inward places of the Bladder, did dilate the skin thereof by its inſited Elatery in the falling down of the Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver. Likewiſe it appears, that that Air which was preſſed to the inward Superficies of the Vial by the Metallick weight, and did ſtay incloſed in the outward folds of the Veſicle, was enough by the vertue of the ſame Elatery to fill the whole Vial.</p>
                           <p>Neither let my Adverſaries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the heavineſs of the Quick-ſilver while it fill'd the Vial
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170048:56"/>did quite thruſt forth the Air; The contiguity of dry things doth not exclude the Air, whoſe outrooting is onely done by glew; In other things there is either Air, or both the Superficies adhere; ſo boys wet leather, by whoſe force they elevat, and weigh up, and throw forth the hanging weight of heavy ſtones. Neither do Liquors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves altogether go away; beat together the wet palms of your hands with as great force as you can, notwithſtanding the humour remaining in the inward boſome of the skin will not evaniſh for any preſſure; Glaſs by nature is ſmooth, nevertheleſs it is poliſhed byart; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the whitiſh ſilver-ſhining of Quick-ſilver argue its moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſmoothneſs. Truly the weight of the Metal bruiſing the ſides of the glaſſy poroſities, the Air, as I have ſaid, being freed by the falling down of the Metal, doth diſplay it ſelf by its proper Elatery in every place within the Pipe.</p>
                           <p>May be you will infer, The Air
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170048:57"/>by the iritating of the Quick-ſilver falling tumultuouſly, doth become fit for dilatation. So alſo would I think, except the unmov'd ſtability of the Glaſſy walls ſhould ſeem to gainſtand her courſe downwards, and ſhould rather roul down thoſe ſliding parts of the Quick-ſilver, which are contiguous to the Glaſs, towards the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than ſuffer them to fall down perpendicularly. So the brinks of the ſhore reſtrain the ſides of thoſe ſtreams which glide a pace in the midſt of their Chanels. So the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of Tunnels onely granteth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of flowing to theſe whirling Liquors in the middle pool onely of the falling ſtream, and likewiſe to the grane in the Milhopper, if you have taken notice of it.</p>
                           <p>I ſhould have admired the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable violence of the skipping beatings within the Pipe, except the Air which then was outwardly incumbent on the Quick-ſilver of the Veſſel D, and whoſe ſubſtance is eaſy to be compreſs'd, being
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170048:57"/>compell'd to give place to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier weight of the body ruſhing down from the top of the Vial, had not made me ſuſpect the Air it ſelf by the repercuſſion of its Elaſtick or dilating vertue even to recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the jumps of the Quick-ſilver within the Pipe it ſelf, till at laſt the eſſays of it incloſed within the Pipe be not overcome with the weight of the Quick-ſilver.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>The ſecond Experiment.</hi> The divers falling of Quick-ſilver according to the ſundry heights of a Hill, proveth that the lower parts of the Air by degrees are more compact than thoſe that lean on them.</head>
                           <p>NEither believe thou that I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the matter with unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpeeches, when I ſay the Earth is preſs'd by the Air; I have a moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent witneſs, the moſt ſubtil <hi>Paſcalius</hi> the ſon, who firſt among our French did, not onely with Quick-ſilver, but
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170048:58"/>other Liquors alſo, raiſe up the Experiment concerning Vacuity, ſcarcely being well born, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſuffocate amongſt ſtrangers; yea with ſuch a ſucceſs of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull induſtry he carried it up, that he did put in all the Devota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of true wiſdome through all <hi>Europe</hi> an eager deſire to try the Experiments of Vacuity.</p>
                           <p>By his care there was lately an Experiment tried in <hi>Avernia,</hi> at the root of the high Mountain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Le puy de Domme,</hi> near the City of <hi>Claramont,</hi> Quick-ſilver being poured into a Pipe four foot long, almoſt like that which we have deſcrib'd above, it did fall down to the third half line of the twenty ſeventh inch above the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfice of the Quick-ſilver ſtanding in the undermoſt Veſſel. Aſcending then the Region of the Mountain, which was about an hundred and fifty paces higher than the roots thereof, the Cylinder of the Quick-ſilver which remained in the Pipe poſſeſs'd the length but of twenty
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:170048:58"/>five inches. At length coming to the top of the Hill, at leaſt five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred paces higher than the root, the ſame Cylinder of the Quick-ſilver found his bound of reſt and height in the ſecond line of the twenty fourth inch; and ſo from the loweſt roots of the Mountain to the higheſt top thereof, it was ſhortned the length of three inches, and half a degree, <hi>viz.</hi> the Air which incompaſs'd the top be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lighter, by reaſon of leſs preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, than that about the middle and root of the Mountain, ought alſo to hold up a ſhorter Cylinder of Quick-ſilver, according to the equality of the balance.</p>
                           <p>Neither wonder thou that this Experiment doth not agree with thoſe that I tried in <hi>Paris</hi> by fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Quick-ſilver: For both the difference of the foot of meaſure in <hi>Avernia</hi> from ours, which it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds in ſome lines (which I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly obſerved) and the divers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Places may be from the Center of the World (even thou
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170048:59"/>being Judge) may not keep equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in theſe Experiments.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>The third Experiment.</hi> The equality of weight of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Air with the internal Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linder of the Quick-ſilver, is ſhewn.</head>
                           <p>IT pleaſeth me alſo, leſt the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born opinion thou haſt of the Antients ſhould murmure againſt my reaſons, whereby I have aſſerted the equality of weight of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Air, and internal Quick-ſilver, to teach the Experiment of Vacuity in Vacuity, firſt happily tried by the ſagacity of the acute <hi>Auzotius.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>assorted vials</figDesc>
                              <p>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>A</item>
                                    <item>B</item>
                                    <item>C</item>
                                    <item>D</item>
                                    <item>E</item>
                                    <item>F</item>
                                    <item>G</item>
                                 </list>
                              </p>
                           </figure>
                           <p>The Air preſſeth downward the Quick-ſilver in E A, by reaſon of the changed equall weight of the outward Air and incloſed Quick-ſilver, proceeding from the increaſe of adventitious Air entred by G: It thruſteth it upwards into C F, becauſe the reſtor'd endeavour of the compreſſory vertue ſearcheth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly after an equall weight.</p>
                           <p>What then, Reader, is to be concluded from theſe things? The outward Air ballanceth the Cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the interiour Quickſilver A E, therefore the Air even in its own ſphere, as they call it, is weighty.</p>
                           <p>The parts of the Air in the Pipe and Carps Bladder are diſtended by their own ſpontaneous dilatation; therefore the inſited Elatery of the ſubſtance of the Air to rarifie it ſelf, doth imitate the nature of a Sponge or Wool.</p>
                           <p>And ſo the thicker the Air is, as hath been manifeſt in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170048:61"/>Experiment, and that of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity in Vacuity, inſomuch it acteth on all ſides with a greater and ſtronger Elatery invading the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfice of the Earth-watriſh Globe.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>The fourth Experiment.</hi> The Water onely by its weight com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the Earth-watry Globe; But the Air compreſſeth it, not onely by its weight, but by its Elatery.</head>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>assorted vials</figDesc>
                              <p>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>A</item>
                                    <item>B</item>
                                    <item>C</item>
                                    <item>D</item>
                                    <item>E</item>
                                 </list>
                              </p>
                           </figure>
                           <p>Hence it clearly appears, that Water onely by its weight, and by no endeavour of an Elatery, as 'tis heavy to Quick-ſilver within the Pipe, ſo it is to the ſuperfice of the Earthly lump.</p>
                           <p>But the vertue of the Air is far more excelient; for if over again
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170048:63"/>eſſaying the Experiment, you fill up, not with Water, but Air, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſpace of ſeven inches C A, that is, if you ſhut up with your finger the Pipe from the Quick-ſilver B C, to the mouth A, being onely full of Air for the ſpace of ſeven inches C A, being afterwards overturned and dìpp'd in the Engin D, you ſhall admire to ſee the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linder of Quick-ſilver A E to be lower by ſeven inches under the twenty ſeventh inch. So that it clearly appeareth, that as the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Quick-ſilver, ſo the Earth-watry Globe is not ſo much preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the weight, as by the Elatery of the Air.</p>
                           <p>I would have you note, that when I ſaid the Cylinder of the Quick-ſilver reſted at the twenty ſeventh inch within the Pipe, I ſpoke then according to the moſt frequent Experiments; For the place of reſt changeth in the Pipe according to the divers changes of the external Air in its rarefactions and condenſations.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170048:63"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The Engins drawn to the aſſiſtance of Attraction, are demoliſhed.</head>
                        <p>HAving demonſtrated by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments conquering all ſtifneſs, and ſubduing all belief, That, more than in a wool heap, the heaping up of the intricate parts in the Air, and the Elater innate therein for rarefaction doth beat the Globe of Water and Earth; I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to examine their Engins who advance <hi>Attraction.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>That the Water entreth into Water-works, not for fear of Vacuity, but by neceſſity of an equal weight is cleared by the period of the Waters aſcent in them, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments.</head>
                           <p>And firſt indeed the office of the ſucker in the Pump, which they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem the greateſt, is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: For they believe our opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is overthrown, and that we
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170048:64"/>have nothing to object, when they have attributed to the Heart the worthy name of the <hi>Vital Anilia:</hi> For as, ſay they, the riſing Clack ſucketh the Water, and falling down beateth it back; So the Heart by the gaping Diaſtole by drawing the Blood ſuppeth it up, which in the preſſure of the Syſtole it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth to depart.</p>
                           <p>The mention of <hi>Anilias</hi> is ſo common in the Mechanicks, which ſome call ſucking in, that none is ignorant of their office when he hears their names: But howſoever the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>uſe in drawing up Liquor is frequent, not any as yet hath found out, in an inſtrument of ſo great uſe, the true inciter or genuine cauſe of its liquid motion.</p>
                           <p>The Inventers, and all thoſe that afterwards have been occupied in Water-works, believ'd that the Water is drawn and ſuck'd up by the riſing of the Clack, which whiles it riſeth raiſeth up the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and accelerateth them for fear of vacuity to riſe upward againſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170048:64"/>their falling nature: But I will ſhew by the following reaſons whether they think well or no.</p>
                           <p>The Earth-watry Globe is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd on all ſides, not onely by the weight of the Air, as we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but likewiſe by the moſt ſtrong endeavour of the Elatery innate in it: Therefore where the heaping of the Aerial parts doth equally act in the ſubject Waters, it ſhall alſo be right that their emulous ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies ſhould remain in the ballance of equall hight.</p>
                           <p>But if the endeavours of the Air be unequall, 'tis neceſſary alſo that the ſuperficies of the Waters ſhould become unequall; So that the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhould riſe higher, where the preſſure of the Air is lighter; and ſo long it ſhould elevate its ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, till the riſing heap of VVater, together with the Air which it ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, ſhould equally ballance that other Air which is of more heavy preſſure.</p>
                           <p>'Tis eaſy for thee to be taught this in a Bucket mechanically.</p>
                           <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170048:65"/>
                           <figure>
                              <p>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>A</item>
                                    <item>B</item>
                                    <item>C</item>
                                    <item>D</item>
                                    <item>E</item>
                                    <item>F</item>
                                    <item>G</item>
                                 </list>
                              </p>
                              <head>Situla</head>
                           </figure>
                           <p>And this is the incitement of the aſcending VVater in the Pump.</p>
                           <p>Before you place in the Pipe of the Pump, ſtanding now in the VVater, the Clack, the Elaſtick (inforcing) weight of the Air beateth no leſs the inward than outward VVater: VVhence it comes to paſs, that the Superficies of the VVater both without and within the Pipe is of the ſame altitude: But when the Clack is fitted to the Pipe, and is lifted upwards, it together with it heaveth up the Pillar of Air which
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170048:66"/>is perpendicularly ſtayed thereon: Hence all weight within the Pipe is taken away, and then the VVa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is urged ſharplier by the perpetual preſſure of the outward Air leaning thereon, ruſheth into the eaſy Pipe; ſo long aſcending till it come to two and thirty foot height, and there at laſt it is of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall weight with the circumfus'd Air.</p>
                           <p>Neither will the Rule of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſure [if we believe experience] ſuffer the ſuperfice of the VVaters ſpringing within the Pipe or Pump, though the Clack ſhould be ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, to aſcend higher.</p>
                           <p>You may likewiſe marveil at this in Quick-ſilver. For the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linder of Quick-ſilver inwardly will not aſcend more than twenty ſeven inches above the ſuperfice of it which ſtandeth in the Veſſel, in either Pump or Pipe: For indeed that Cylinder of Quick-ſilver doth counterpoſe, a heap of water of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two and thirty feet, in weight.</p>
                           <p>None of the VVater ariſeth above
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170048:66"/>thirty two foot, none of the Quick-ſilver above twenty ſeven inches, though the Clack be drawn up with the greateſt force of the Pipe: Therefore neither fear of Vacuity, who in the higheſt places of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould offer it ſelf, moveth the VVaters to follow: Neither the endeavour of the Air, which is ſpent with ſo little force of Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure doth oppreſs the Earth-watry Globe with its infuſed Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</p>
                           <p>Hence let all VVater-workers take notice, and all thoſe Craftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who hope by the benefit of ear'd Syphons to draw VVater over the tops of intermediate Hils, that the Hill be not above two and thirty foot high above the Spring, otherwiſe they ſhall loſe their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. The ſame judgement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning drawing, as they call them, Pumps, is firm and ſtable. I omit other Pumps, and eſpecially thoſe in which the Clack like a Bucket is dipped in the VVater to draw it up; For the elevate VVater receives no
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170048:67"/>period of aſcent in their Pipes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept what is preſcrib'd by the force of that power that moves the Clack: Yea they have not any buſineſs with the fear of Vacuity or of the Air.</p>
                           <p>Seeing therefore that the VVa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter haſteth into the Pump, not by the incitement of <hi>Attraction,</hi> but by the Elaſtick heavineſs of the ſpread-about Air, there is no reaſon why we ſhould ſpend any longer time in refelling the Argúments which our Adverſaries draw from this Engin, to prove the <hi>Attraction</hi> of the Heart.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>That Bellows do not draw the Air, but onely receive it thruſt in them from without.</head>
                           <p>Neither will the Heart more happily prove <hi>Sucking</hi> or <hi>Attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> by playing the part of Bellows. A pair of Bellows do neither ſuck nor draw the Air to them, but are compell'd to receive it being thruſt in by external violence.</p>
                           <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170048:67"/>
                           <p>The Air liyng hid within the lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king places of the folded and cloſed Bellowes, is of the ſame Elatery (that is, Spontaneous dilatation) that the circumfus'd external Air is of; and ſo the reſting of the equal weight contains both unmoved; Whiles you diſtend the Bellowes, even then the inward Air [as was made clear in the Bladder of a Pearch] of its own Spontaneous dilatation, which is therefore more weaker, it would ratifie, except a more ſtrong force of an outward Air did compell the Air next their Pipe without, and any liquid thing that is within, to equal ballance.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>The force of Aerial dilatation, which it hath from its proper Elatery, doth languiſh, but by an external cauſe becometh firm.</head>
                           <p>Neither let any man with more ſucceſsful Eloquence perſwade me of the <hi>Attraction</hi> of <hi>Aeolipilaes</hi> and <hi>Cupping Glaſſes,</hi> proceeding of the effect produc'd by the Fire; and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170048:68"/>that thou mayſt more eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how deſervedly I oppoſe it, hear my opinion concerning the buſineſs of Heat.</p>
                           <p>Indeed the leaſt Heat doth dilate the Air, as no man doubteth; But with this difference from that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latation whereby it is ſometimes of it ſelf freely dilated, That the Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneous dilatation enerveth the power of the Elaſtick (impulſive) faculty, as the Experiments of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity in Vacuity, and the Carps Bladder do demonſtrate; But the other, which is extraneous to the Air, <hi>viz.</hi> from the acceſſion of heat, will make it firm, and will aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment its growing, and is found by little and little to remit in its lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <pb n="123" facs="tcp:170048:68"/>
                           <head>The Weather-Glaſs doth demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that not onely the Air, but that the Water alſo is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the acceſſion of Heat.</head>
                           <p>So the Hand or a Coal put upon the upward Bottle of a Weather-Glaſs, cauſeth the water therein contained to deſcend; A great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that the Air which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated within doth in force excell the deſcending water which it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth to give it place.</p>
                           <p>Neither doth the onely Air pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce its own ends by the incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Heat; Yea the heap of water is likewiſe extended thereby.</p>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>depiction of thermostat</figDesc>
                              <p>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>A</item>
                                    <item>B</item>
                                    <item>C</item>
                                 </list>
                              </p>
                           </figure>
                           <p>I preſcribe no Law to the water to be hung in C; for oft-times I have found it by chance hanging, and not a little diſtant from the water in B in the under Veſſel, which by the diligence of my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour I could have brought to paſs.</p>
                           <p>The Air growing cold in A, the water floweth upward, for the Elaſtick vertue of this, as it imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the increments of Heat, ſo likewiſe it obſerveth the changes of the deficiencies in the ſame.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>How the Fleſh and Blood is thruſt into the Cupping-Glaſſes.</head>
                           <p>The kindled fire doth thruſt out of the Cupping-Glaſs the greateſt part of the rarified Air; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by the Cupping-Glaſs preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hard to the skin, ſo that no external Air can enter [becauſe of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170048:70"/>the ſtopping of the motion may be of the Fiery Spirits hindred by the Glaſs] it is extinguiſhed; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Heat doth languiſh, which the motion of the Fiery Spirits did ſuſtain: At laſt the Air within the Cupping-Glaſs becometh cold, and that ſtrength of it being weakned, which the heat raiſed, being feeble 'tis overcome by the ſtrength of the outward Air. Which external Air, to conclude, compreſſing in all places equally the body, except that ſpace that is contain'd in the Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Glaſs, doth thruſt into it the Fleſh and Blood, as the Liquor into the Pumps.</p>
                           <p>Adde, that thoſe Aerial parts which poſſeſs the porous lurking places of the body, neither do they leſs lye in wait for Dilation than Externals watch by Elatery to raiſe the obedient Fleſh and Blood into a tumor. For whiles the Air in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd in the Cupping-Glaſs begins to wax cold, and by this means its endeavours become leſs, then the Air, which wandreth in the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170048:70"/>Pores of the Fleſh, being deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of its trouble, raiſeth the skin into a little tumor by its Sponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Elatery.</p>
                           <p>But Snow, ſay ſome, or any cold thing cramb'd in the Cucurbite, hindreth its commerce with the Fleſh; and on the other ſide a Linnen Cloth a little hotter put thereon, as Chirurgions do, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth up the Attraction; Wherefore the Elaſtick force of the Air clos'd within the Cupping-Glaſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh not dull with cold.</p>
                           <p>But I know not out of what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention they object that which I have found not once altogether contrary to Experience. For I have oft put Water, yea Snow, on a Cupping-Glaſs applied to the Fleſh, but the inward Air was with ſuch ſwiftneſs condens'd, that the Fleſh ſuddenly grew into a little tumor not without moſt great pain; But ſo ſoon as I had covered the Cucurbite with a very hot Linnen Cloth, preſently the pain did remit, and the tumor diminiſh.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170048:71"/>'Tis then no wonder that the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions caſt ſuch a Linnen Cloth over the Cupping-Glaſſes, leſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould ſtir up more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement pain, or raiſe the Fleſh to too great a tumor, or draw out the Blood in too great abundance.</p>
                           <p>Neither believe thou that with this ſucceſs I have applied a Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-Glaſs onely to live Bodies, yea I have applied it to Carkaſſes and Liquors. And indeed put into Boyling Water a Cupping-Glaſs, you will admire to ſee a heap of Water crept into it, the Fire being altogether extinguiſhed, or the Heat become Luke-warm; and if then you apply to the Cupping-Glaſs a Cloth dipp'd in any Cold Liquor, or Snow it ſelf, or Ice, the inward Air contracting it ſelf, and its Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery being debilitated by the Cold, a greater abundance of Water ſhall be thruſt into the Cupping-Glaſs.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <pb n="129" facs="tcp:170048:71"/>
                           <head>How Water is thruſt into the hot Aeolipila.</head>
                           <p>So Aeolipilaes [Wind-balls or Globes made of Copper, with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals going out of them, which Glaſs-makers uſe inſtead of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes] being placed in the midſt of a Fire, exhale moſt of the Air they contain; and then as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of the Air within grows cold, and the force of the Elatery being weakned, the external prevailing Air haſtneth the Water into the Engin by its Tail-pipe dipp'd therein; and that with no little force, as we diſcern by the noyſe of its murmuring.</p>
                           <p>And hence likewiſe falleth to the Ground the Prop of the <hi>Attractive Opinion</hi> rais'd by Heat.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <pb n="130" facs="tcp:170048:72"/>
                           <head>Other waies of drawing Air out of Aeolipilaes are propos'd and explain'd.</head>
                           <p>There is another way of filling Aeolipilaes, <hi>viz.</hi> by out-ſucking; a ſtrong argument againſt our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, if indeed it were firm, which all have already believ'd, <hi>That the Air when we ſuck is drawn backwards to the Throat.</hi> It pleaſeth me therefore to explain this <hi>Myſterie.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Cloſe the Tail of an Aeolipila in thy Mouth, ſo that the Air con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in both places may become continued in the ſame Cloſet of the Mouth; Indeed ſo long as the Tongue is not moved, nor the Breaſt enlarged, and the Air likewiſe in both places [to wit, in the Mouth and Aeolipila] quiet, doth perſevere in the Law of equal poiſure. But where there is either Motion in Tongue or Breaſt, 'tis needfull that in both places the Air is moved: and becauſe by one of the Motions
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170048:72"/>at leaſt the Aeolipila is emptied, it pleaſeth me to enquire after what manner this is perfected.</p>
                           <p>Either uſe onely the Lungs, or the Bellowes-like dilatation of the Breaſt, or the beating onely of the Sucking Tongue, as they believe, againſt the Palate.</p>
                           <p>By the firſt way indeed the whole Breaſt is diſtended, in the mean time no breath of exteriour Air en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in either by the ſhut-lips, neither by the breathing holes of the noſtrils either to the Mouth, or to the Aeolipila. The diſtended Breaſt likewiſe prepares a more ample place for the Air, which is contain'd by the den of the Mouth, contiguous to the Aeolipilary Air. The Air having receiv'd room ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it ſelf towards the Breaſt, and therefore the Elater of it becometh more weak than that of the Aeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipilar; which when this [to wit, clos'd within the Aeolipila] per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, and that it is repreſs'd by the endeavours of none, it rarifies it ſelf, and it doth propagate its
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170048:73"/>bounds without the Aeolipila, as the force of the weaker will ſuffer it.</p>
                           <p>But by the latter manner, the whole Tongue, together with the Pipe of the Aeolipila, doth more compactly beat againſt the whole Palate; Then the middle of the obſequious Tongue ſinking to the door of the little Pipe, forſaketh the Palate, and by a more ſharp endeavour doth fold it ſelf into a Furrow; So that of that force the ſpace that is obnoxious to the Aeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipilar Air, not being empty indeed, but full with the little Air which had remained below the cavernous Cuticles of the Tongue and Palate, ſollicitateth the Elatery of the ſame (I mean of the Aeolipilar) Air to dilatation, and allures and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viteth this Spontaneous Elatery out of the Aeolipila into the Furrow of the Mouth; and doth not, as our Adverſaries believe, compell it by drawing.</p>
                           <p>When ſo much of the Air hath flow'd out of the Aeolipila both
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170048:73"/>wayes as could, by the preſſure of the external Air which is then more thick than the internal, the Water ſhall ſo long run into the Engin by the Tail ſuddenly dipp'd in the Water, till a juſt counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſe ſhall give reſt to the equal ſtrength of both that's without and within.</p>
                           <p>After the ſame manner ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thou ſuckedſt; after the ſame manner Children plunder the Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hogſheads by ſtealth, dipping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Drinking Reeds; yea by the ſame way fill the Syihons with Liquor, <hi>viz.</hi> by the weight and endeavour of the outward Air, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the flowing of the Liquors according to the dilatation of the Throat or Mouth.</p>
                           <p>Thus having demoliſh'd the chief Engins whereby our Adverſaries e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh their <hi>Attraction,</hi> I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to ſpend no more time in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous matters.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="134" facs="tcp:170048:74"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The true Cauſes of the Blood's Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are diſcovered.</head>
                        <p>HAving demonſtrated what a light incitement the weight of innate gravity is to the Motion of the Blood, and having obſerv'd by evident Experiments that the Hearts Syſtole ſufficeth not alone for this effect, and having altogether cut off the helps of the <hi>Diaſtolick At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction,</hi> it remaineth that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Conſtruction of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and that we ponder their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion from the Agitation of the neighbouring parts.</p>
                        <p>'Tis certain that the Veſſels are ſtraitned by Spontaneous Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or by Violent.</p>
                        <p>I call that Spontaneous whereby of themſelves they leave their ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fulneſs.</p>
                        <p>I call that Violent which an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Cauſe produceth.</p>
                        <p>I demonſtrate the Spontaneous after this manner.</p>
                        <div type="section">
                           <pb n="135" facs="tcp:170048:74"/>
                           <head>Of the Spontaneous Contraction of the Veſſels.</head>
                           <p>I believe no man doubteth, that the Blood is urg'd out of the Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricles of the Heart, and floweth into the Arteries by a certain force or compreſſion of the Syſtolick Motion; And if at that time the force of its flowing were not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by any ſtops, the Blood was able to return even to the Heart by the endeavour onely of Compreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                           <p>But remember [Reader] that the Blood thruſt into the Arteries by reaſon of its Continuity, ſo thruſt with it the Venoſe Blood, ſo that notwithſtanding nothing flows a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from the Veins into the Heart, till the action of the Syſtoles be quite ended, and the Diaſtoles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun; And for this that not onely the Arteries, but the Veins alſo in the laſt moment of the Syſtoles are turn'd with abundance of two ſorts of Blood, <hi>viz.</hi> with the old and with the new comed.</p>
                           <pb n="136" facs="tcp:170048:75"/>
                           <p>The Tunicles of the Veſſels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then more ſtretched by reaſon of the ſtay of the Blood during the Syſtoles continuance, doth ſtir up the innate Elatery according to the meaſure of its natural capacity, that immediatly ſo ſoon as the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glochinon</hi> Valve had finiſhed his duty by the ſucceeding Diaſtole, ſhould quickly diſcover his power that lay at wait, and ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the compreſs'd Blood to ruſh into the open and empty boſomes of the relaxed Heart.</p>
                           <p>Hence appears what the Sponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Contraction of the Veſſels is: The Violent followeth.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Of the Violent Contraction of the Veſſels.</head>
                           <p>This is rais'd up either by the ſharpneſs of the more piercing humour; ſo the ſharper Bile doth ſtraiten the Inteſtine Membranes into wrinkles, or pricking and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Continuity from what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Cauſe: So when ſometimes
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170048:75"/>I opened the <hi>Duodenum</hi> according to its length making inciſion, that I might obſerve the Liquor flowing out of the Pancreatical Veſſel of <hi>Virſungus</hi> into this Gut, the Gut did ſo wrinkle it ſelf, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted the inciſion to the middle; and cloſing up the little entrance of <hi>Virſungus</hi> his Canale, did alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſtop the running watriſh humour which flowed from thence. And the ſame judgement which belongeth to the Guts is to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the other Veſſels and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes of the Body.</p>
                           <p>The Contraction of Veſſels after this manner may be brought to paſs by the help of Ligatures, <hi>viz.</hi> the pricking of Pain, being Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the ſtraitneſſes of the Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, do ſolicitate all the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring parts to the help of the diſeaſed; and whilſt they concurr to the ſpending of their obſequious Blood, where the Valve doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, the Veſſels become wrinkled. Hence the Blood in the Veins haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth from the Ligature to the Heart;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170048:76"/>but that in the Arteries haſtneth to the Extreme Parts, the Valves admitting it, whereof ſome indeed forbid regreſs by another way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſtoppages.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Of the Compreſſion of the Veſſels.</head>
                           <p>But ſo far as belongeth to the Compreſſary Coarctation of the Veſſels, I ſay the ſame is perfected both by the preſſure of breath'd Air into the Lungs, and by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour of the Muſcles adjacent to the Pipes whilſt they are ſtirr'd.</p>
                           <p>So a more vehement motion maketh the Pulſe beat ſwiftlier, and produceth a more frequent blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo the quaking tumult of the leaping parts in a dying Creature, proceeding from the Cold falling on them, doth empty the Arteries, the Veins remaining full.</p>
                           <p>Therefore I ſay the Blood is Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated by a three-fold incitement, <hi>viz.</hi> by the Impulſion of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoles; by the Contraction of the Veſſels, whether Violent or Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary;
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170048:76"/>and by the Endeavour of the Adjacent Parts, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of their Veſſels: Theſe three are ſo diſpoſed towards one another, that ſome of them ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more recompenſeth the defect of the other, though ſlowly, by the perſeverance of his duty. While the Heart doth beat, it doth out of it ſelf thruſt the Blood into the Veins and Arteries; The Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of its own Tunicle doth em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty the tyed Artery beyond the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gature; The Contraction of the Vicine Parts gives aſſiſtance to this effect; The Tumor of the tyed Vein beyond the Ligature, that is, betwixt it and the Extreme Parts, is intended by the Continual mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Blood which the Arteries, being free of a Ligature, iſſue out; On this ſide the Ligature, that is, towards the Heart, the Evacuation is perfected by the Contraction of the Tunicle, and preſſure of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine Parts.</p>
                           <p>And ſo the Blood is preſs'd out of the Heart into the Arteries; it
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170048:77"/>is tunned partly out of the Arteries into the Veins by the Synanaſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſies, partly 'tis poured out into the Fleſh, and from thence gather'd into the Veins, it returneth again into the Heart in a Circle ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Life, that being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo little hindred, either Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or Swouning, and not ſeldom alſo Death followes thereon.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:170048:77"/>
                     <head>OF THE MOTION OF THE CHYLE.</head>
                     <div n="11" type="chapter">
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> It is demonſtrated, that the Chyle is alſo thruſt into the Lacteal Veins, and is driven towards the Heart, and that it is not ſucked.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Motion of the Blood being perfected, it may eaſily alſo be ſhewn whither the Chyle is roled.</p>
                        <p>All know that the Chyle is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd from the Aliments that fall into the Inteſtines from the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack which concocteth them, and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170048:78"/>that they go through the Tunicles of the Inteſtins by the little Pores opened by Nature into the Pipes of the Lacteal Veins, But whether the Pervious Inteſtins imitate a Sive or a Sponge, their double Coat (which is proper to them) doth not denote any one of them, but them both. Nature hath wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven their outmoſt coat with the threds of moſt ſmall Fibers artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, like a ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aining Sieve, unto which by her providence with a wonderful anointing ſhe hath glewed on the inſide a wrinkling or ſpongeous, if you will, lining, of a moſt ſoft ſubſtance; that both the ſharpneſs of the Aliments may paſs unhurting them; and that that juice which is moſt ſubtil may be ſtrain'd out of the Excrements into the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteal Veins.</p>
                        <p>The former Experiments clearly ſhewed the paſſage of the Chyle; now we are to ſearch whether the Chyle is thruſt or drawn.</p>
                        <div type="section">
                           <pb n="143" facs="tcp:170048:78"/>
                           <head>That the Chyle is not drawn.</head>
                           <p>The Chyle is not drawn or ſucked; for whether you bind in the Meſentery the Lacteal Veins, or whether you put a Ligature on the ſame, within the Cheſt of the Breaſt beyond the Ligature, that is, towards the Inteſtins ſwelling up, they will ſuffocate the Attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory or ſucking opinion.</p>
                           <p>Neither affirm thou that the Lacteals, like Blood-ſuckers, do draw the Chyle by ſucking: For the Blood-ſuckers do not draw the Blood, neither do they otherwiſe draw out the ſame, than we, when putting a Reed into a Spring or Hogſhead, we draw out the Liquor by the diſtention both of Mouth and Lungs; for the Blood-ſuckers do prick the Cutaneous Veins, and whiles they ſwell, by the labour of the Lungs playing the part of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, by their dilatation the Blood entreth into their eaſy Stomacks. Therefore the Chyle is not thruſt
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170048:79"/>forwards into the Lacteal Veins, but it comes to be inquir'd of whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the proper action of the Inteſtins, or by a vertue extraneous to them.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Of the Contraction of the Inteſtins.</head>
                           <p>When the Chyle or Juice fried out of the meat ſlideth from the Stomack into the Guts, it tumifieth them, and doth extend their Fibers moſt obſequious-like into an Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery: So that their vigour being augmented by intenſion, returning again of their own will to their natural eſtate, they ſtraiten the Guts by depreſſing the Chyle from the Stomack to the Fundament. And hence I conclude, The Guts, like ſome Membranous Bodies, have their proper Contraction, but an Extraneous dilatation.</p>
                           <p>Beſides this Contraction you are to obſerve the dilatation and wrinklings of the Spongeous Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane which is within the Guts: For that Tunicle drinking up the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170048:79"/>more fluid juice of the Chyle that ſlipped out of the Stomack, doth ſwell as a Sponge; and when 'tis wrinkled by either the Compreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the adjacent parts; or ſome other Cauſe, partly it removes the Chyle inwardly, partly it doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it into the Lacteal Veins.</p>
                           <p>Moreover, you are to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, That that Contraction of the Inteſtins, and wrinkling of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Membrane, ſucceedeth the extraneous dilatation, and that it little or nothing avails for the thruſting of Chyle into the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteal Veins, yea rather that it much ſtoppeth its paſſage: For the Gut the more Contracted it is, the more it ſtoppeth the Pores, and therefore the open ends of the Lacteal Veins, and giveth a leſs pervious paſſage to the inclos'd Liquors. And this alſo is taken notice of above in the violent Contraction of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and eaſy Experience doth prove, it both in other Membranes, and moſt in the Bladder new pull'd
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170048:80"/>out of the body; For indeed 'tis contracted, the piſs flowing out; neither will it then being prickt up and down with a Needle, ſhed any of the Urine out of the Needle holes, except by compreſſing it violently you wring the Liquor out of it.</p>
                           <p>So the Periſtaltick motion of the Guts, if any ſuch be to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, for it was not any where diſcovered to us in Living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, becauſe it ſucceſſively draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth together their Coats, cloſing with wrinkling the paſſages, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to thruſt the Chyle into the Lacteals; Except may be you joyn to it the other motion of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latation, by which, while it doth corrugate the upper part of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trals together with it, it diſtends the inferiour, which being filled with meats, it may iſſue through it a greater deal of Chyle into the Lacteals.</p>
                           <p>But ſeeing that dilatation, which is produc'd from the falling down Chyle, is of little force, and ſcarce
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170048:80"/>opens thoſe little Pores wherein the Chyle is thruſt, indeed we are at laſt to arrive at a more vehement Compreſſion of the Guts.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Of the Compreſſion of the Guts.</head>
                           <p>I find amongſt the firſt a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Cauſe of this, <hi>viz.</hi> Reſpiration, and a Contraction of the Muſcles in the Belly and Breaſt; ſuch an one chiefly as is ſtirr'd up by the emptying of the Excrements out of the Guts, and unburthening of the Bladder, and may be of evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Gall. For then the Air inclos'd in the Lungs which they draw in, and the vehement endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Muſcles do not a little compreſs the Intrals: So that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve by that motion the Chyle is expreſs'd out of the Stomack into the Guts, and that this white ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance breaketh out of the Guts into the Lacteal Veins.</p>
                           <p>I paſs by that Contraction and Dilatation, by whoſe means the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170048:81"/>Muſcles of Reſpiration are ſtirr'd up by a Continued motion; For they do not ſo Compreſs the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trals that they are able to expreſs the Chyle out of the Guts. I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the beating of the Arteries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Guts; for the Arteries being quiet after the tying of the Coeliack Branch, the ſliding-in Chyle doth no leſs tumifie the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteal Veins. It onely remains then that we fly to the vehement Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of the Muſcles, or to the Continual Viciſſitude of Breathing outward and inward.</p>
                           <p>But becauſe the perpetual paſſing of the Chyle, ſo long as Aliments remain, requireth likewiſe a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Cauſe of Compreſſion, which in vain is ſought in that all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Momentary Contraction of the Muſcles: We are in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at laſt to fly to the Viciſſitudes of Breathings.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:170048:81"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>OF RESPIRATION.</hi> 'Tis declar'd how Reſpiration is wrought, and what it availeth the Motion of the Chyle. That the Lungs are not a pervious Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, is known by Experiments.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eſpiration is done, as is known to all, by the Alternal Elatery of the Lungs and Air, ſo as by the dilatation of the Air, which is receiv'd and rarified by the heat of the Lungs, the Lungs together with the Muſcles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration are diſtended, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by their Spontaneous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction the Air it ſelf is compell'd to go out.</p>
                     <pb n="150" facs="tcp:170048:82"/>
                     <p>But the diſtention of Lungs in fetching breath, which the open wounds of the Breaſt declare, is an Argument, That their Tunicle is altogether impervious. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed 'tis more compact, neither ever will it give leave to the Air to go through them by any force or breathing.</p>
                     <p>Theſe things will be manifeſted by Experiments. If you blow with an Oat-reed into the <hi>Bronchia</hi> [Wind-pipe] of a Living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whilſt you are cutting it up: For uſe what means you can, the Wind will not touch the flame of the Candle you hold to it, except in that place you have opened the Coat thereof.</p>
                     <p>Here you are to take notice, That Chirurgions oft-times erre in the wounds of the Breaſt; They hold near to them the flame of a Candle, and by its motion, which is procur'd by the Air breathing out thereat, they fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inferre, That the Lungs are
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170048:82"/>wounded. But if they ſhall reply any thing, then in Empyick ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations they may be bold to averre the rupture of the Lungs from the like mobility of the flame.</p>
                     <p>Neither ſhould you eſteem the Tunicle of the Lungs porous by the matter of a Pleuriſy avoyded by Screation or urine. For as our <hi>Riolan</hi> hath exactly ſet down in the third Book and fourth Chapter of his <hi>Encheiridion, There is no ſuch effluxion, except the Pleura be burſt, and the Lungs excoriate; viz.</hi> if either before the Pleuriſy they ſtuck to the Ribs, or whiles the inflammation begins to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, the Lungs ſticking to the Pleura, both by the Glew of the Viſcous humour ſwearing out by the Phlegmones heat, and by the ſmallneſs of the motion, hindred by the pain and tumor, they are joyn'd together. For the Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone then touching both the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes Infects both together with rottenneſs turning into an Ulcer:
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170048:83"/>Whence it comes to paſs, that the Matter ruſhing into the Lungs, is either thrown out by the Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe in Spittel, or is carried by the Venal Artery into the left Ventricle of the Heart, and thence going into the <hi>Aorta</hi> it goes through the Reins, and is avoyded with the Urine.</p>
                     <p>What, ſay you, if there be no Contiguity of Membranes, the Pleura nevertheleſs will burſt, will the Atter remain in the bottome of the Breaſt? It will altogether remain, even to the undoing of the party, except by the quickly open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Empyema</hi> you empty it of this Purulent burthen.</p>
                     <p>But I return to Reſpiration, in which whilſt the Pulmons are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, they alſo preſs the Midriff downward; and the Liver, which then plays the part of a Piſtil acting by the weight of its bulk beating by intervals, doth not onely compell the Chyle to depart out of the Stomack through the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170048:83"/>Pylore into the Guts, but alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtends their little Pores, and thence thruſts into the Lacteal Veins the moſt ſubtil ſubſtance of the Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So Children gripe with their hands an Ele-skin full of water, and through the little holes with the ſmall point of a Needle made therein every where, by preſſing it they cauſe the water to ſpring forth into many ſmall ſtreams.</p>
                     <p>But becauſe our ſpeech is arrived at the depreſſion of the Diaphragm, it will not be beſides our purpoſe to declare all I have obſerved con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terning its Motion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:170048:84"/>
                     <head>OF THE MOTION OF THE DIAPHRAGM.</head>
                     <p>VVHilſt the Lungs draw in the Air, by little and little ſwelling at that middle of the Diaphragm where it is tyed to the back, they drive downward the deſcending fibers of this middle, which in the Circumference indeed are fleſhy, but membranous in the Center, and by their palpitation compreſs the inferiour places of the Stomack hanging under, together with the Liver: But indeed the other mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, where the Diaphragm is plac'd, under both the Breaſt-bone, and Cartilages of the Baſtard Ribs,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170048:84"/>and doth unfold the membranous Fibers of its Center, and lifteth up obliquely its fleſhy Fibers of the Circumference together with the fore-region of the Breaſt; So that whilſt the hinder parts of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragm are depreſs'd, at the ſame almoſt moment the former parts are lifted up with a vehement ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving indeed.</p>
                     <p>Neither believe thou that thoſe Muſcles in Breaſt and Belly, which they call the Muſcles of Reſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do any way aſſiſt this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for they being quite cut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way even till the Cartilages of the Breaſt-bone be diſcovered [the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercoſtal Muſcles and Diaphragm being preſerv'd] and the den of the inferiour Belly being laid open, nevertheleſs the Creature doth breath as much as if theſe Muſcles were not wounded at all.</p>
                     <p>And theſe are the Motions which I have obſerv'd in Aſpiration [draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Breath] but in Expirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both the fore-parts of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragm
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170048:85"/>together with the Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, do fall, and the hinder-parts, together with Liver and Stomack, doth riſe, and then the Diaphragm is drawn in wrinkles by its Fibers, both in its membranous Center, and fleſhy Circumference.</p>
                     <p>Before I finiſh my ſpeech of the Diaphragm, I would have you take notice of this one thing, That thoſe fleſhy productions of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragm above the Loyns, as it were Appendicles, do lurk under the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle</hi> of the Chyle, ſo that they cannot be diſtended, but together with them diſtending the <hi>Recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> it ſelf, they compell it to iſſue out the Chyle it contains; and theſe are enough of the Diaphragm. We will anſwer the Objections brought againſt our Opinion, aſſerting, That Reſpiration is the ſole inciter of the Chyle into the Lacteal Veins.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:170048:85"/>
                     <head>THE OBJECTIONS AGAINST RESPIRATION Anſwered.</head>
                     <p>VVHy therefore, ſayſt thou, ſhould not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of it ſelf blind thruſt into the Lacteals dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with undigeſted, with pure ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent? Except, Reader, I were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd of Common Opinions, onely to admit that which is voyc'd by the teſtimony of Experience, I would anſwer; Seeing the Lacteal Veins do not immediatly receive the Chyle from the Stomack, for it hath no Lacteals, that Concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is perfected before it comes from the Stomack; and for that whatſoever
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170048:86"/>Aliment deſcends into the Guts moſt ready prepared, that Chyle ſhould be expreſſed out thereof, it cannot become raw by the mixture of any undigeſted ſubſtance.</p>
                     <p>But becauſe many times not a few things do ruſh down out of the Stomach towards the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Bladder, before the finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of requiſite Concoction; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any patent way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Stomack and Bladder, but that of the Lacteals; I am my ſelf compell'd to confeſs, that many times even Crude Aliments do deſcend from the Stomack.</p>
                     <p>And indeed preſently after the immoderate drinking of Wine, a man in Cups ſhall make water; neither doth that limpider Urine which he maketh receive any taſt or tincture. Hence I reaſon, that it hath not flowed through the Maſs of Blood, from which it ſhould have received ſomething of either. The ſtay of Urine in the Body made of Mineral waters,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170048:86"/>is moſt ſhort. The Urine within a quarter of an hour after the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Aſparagus receives its ſwell and colour. Yea the Juice preſs'd out of the Indian Figs makes the Urine become Purple.</p>
                     <p>Therefore I, I ſay, believe, that before the Concoction be finiſh'd, theſe Liquors haſt to the Bladder by the paſſage of the Chyle; the Pylore admitting them either for the urging over-fulneſs, or for the opening force of theſe Diuretick Liquors, or for ſome other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                     <p>Neither object the <hi>Vas breve,</hi> that its poſtern doth empty theſe ſuperfluities in the Milt, and from thence ſpread in the Liver, are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered again, that they may aſcend to the Heart; and afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thruſt into the Arteries, at laſt are thrown headlong by the Emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents into the Reins; For both the ſhortneſs of time doth not agree to ſo great a Circuit, and they through ſo many errours and mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170048:87"/>of humours ſhould not onely receive a tincture, but, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our daily experience, ſhould be ſharpned with ſaltneſs.</p>
                     <p>But if thou ſhouldſt ſuſpect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceivable paſſages from the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make towards the Reins, ſuffer thy ſelf, Reader, not to believe ſuch paſſages, till with their grown greatneſs they leave of to evaniſh out of thy ſight.</p>
                     <p>I would rather believe that theſe Liquors flow out of the Stomack by the Pylorus, and that they are thruſt out of the Guts through the Lacteals unto the <hi>Receptacle</hi> of the Chyle diſcovered by us under the Meſentery; and from thence partly by the Chylous paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Breaſt do flow unto the Heart, the Forge of Blood; partly being ſeparate from the Chyle, do flow into the Reins plac'd on both ſides, either by the Trunk of the Emulgent Arteries ſticking firmly to the <hi>Receptacle</hi> of the Chyle, which perchance for this uſe is
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170048:87"/>thence from without pervious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and fit like a ſtrainer to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colate the ſeroſity: Or if you had rather, they have diverted by the adjacent Miniſtry of the Atrabilar Caſes; or by the Miniſtry of the Peritoneum, whoſe doubling is very ſubject to carry the Liquors, in reſpect of the neighbourhood of the Parts.</p>
                     <p>Truly there appears no fitter way to me for the carrying out of thoſe things which oft-times leave the Stomack not onely without Concoction, but oft-times not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much as hot therein.</p>
                     <p>So, whiles the Air is moſt hot, immoderate drinking of cold water openeth the Belly; The ſame force is in Aſſes Milk, and Mineral Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The Tunicles of Grapes, of Berries, and all the ſlughes of Fruits, Seeds or Pulſes, though never ſo long boyling in the heat of the Stomack, nevertheleſs they are even then thrown out Crude:
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170048:88"/>How much more ſhall they ruſh out of the ſtomach before they be concocted, who are of an apertive and laxative quality? And hence it is, that Medicins being drunk and avoyded by the ſiege, both taſt and ſmell ſometimes with the colour remaining.</p>
                     <p>Your Object again, That the Chyle ruſheth into the Lacteal Veins, even when the ſpirit of the Lungs is ſpent, and the force of breathing altogether extinct: So that opening the Breaſt of a Living Creature, and the Pulmons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming flaccid, nevertheleſs the Lacteal Veins tyed in the Meſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery will ſwell for a little time.</p>
                     <p>Truly 'tis a weighty Argument againſt our opinion; For anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which, I wiſh you to take notice of that, that I have oft tryed, That the Lacteals tyed in the Meſentery, then onely ſwell, when the Living Creature, the Breaſt being unhurt, vehemently doth yet move the whole entrals
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170048:88"/>of the lower Belly, together with the Muſcles of all the body: For when, the Breaſt being opened, the motion of the Animal is extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd, the Lacteals leave off al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to ſwell; except may be the Spongeous Membranes of the Guts, in reſpect of the Colder Air, or pricks of grief, drawing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together, they expreſs a little of the reſidue of that Chyle they before had gathered, into the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteals.</p>
                     <p>I conclude, Therefore Reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration doth thruſt the Chyle into the Lacteals, the other two, <hi>viz.</hi> Contraction and Compreſſion, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting it. This, by the endeavour of the Vicine parts, ſtirreth up the Chyle contain'd both in the Guts, and likewiſe in the Lacteals: But the other is ſuch an Enemy to the fulneſs of the Canals, that it ſuffers not, after death, any footſtep to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main either of Lacteals in the Breaſt or Meſentery, neither of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle</hi> on the Backs Vertebers.</p>
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:170048:89"/>
                     <p>And theſe are the things I had to publiſh concerning the Motion of Blood and Chyle, and of the incitement thereto. It remaineth (Reader) I ſhould take away the Complaint thou haſt in behalf of the Liver, from which I took away the office of making the Blood.</p>
                     <div n="12" type="chapter">
                        <pb n="165" facs="tcp:170048:89"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the Tranſcolatory uſe of the Liver.</head>
                        <p>AFter I have taken from the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that uſurped Glory of Blood-making which undeſervedly it retain'd for ſo many ages; 'tis juſt I ſhould aſſign to it that duty for which it was made, and plac'd in the Forge, as they call it, of the firſt Region, and that I ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe the true office thereof.</p>
                        <p>Beſides that office which it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth, as is ſaid before, inſtead of a Piſtill beating the parts plac'd under it in the Lower Belly by the motion of Reſpiration; The Liver alſo doth, by that great ſtream of Blood it receives from the <hi>Vena porta,</hi> adminiſter Heat to the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack to help the Concoction of the Meat; And moreover, doth ſtrain the Blood through his moſt fit <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renchyma</hi> [Subſtance.] And as the Reins purgeth the Blood of its <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
                           <pb n="166" facs="tcp:170048:90"/>and the Melt of its Acidity, ſo the Liver doth deliver it of the fellowſhip of the Bile that is mixt therewith.</p>
                        <p>For if no ſourſe of Chylous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth come unto it, neither there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the Liver impurpluſh any Aliment into Blood; And onely the Trunk of the <hi>Vena porta</hi> [which likewiſe doth not from any place receive Chyle, as hath been ſhewn] doth fill it with the Blood where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it ſwelleth; Neither doth any man wiſely [if I be any whit wiſe] repute Bile the Excrement of the ſecond Concoction, neither ſhould he eſteem it ſeparable by any other Inſtrument.</p>
                        <p>And indeed you ſhall not find any where, in any kind of Living Creatures, the Blood without the mixture of Bile; The yellowiſh and ſalt <hi>Serum</hi> will teſtifie ſo much: Except perchance in ſome Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to whom meek Miſtris Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath concocted a ſweeter Blood; As in others, in which ſhe
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170048:90"/>hath infus'd Blood without Acidity, whom ſhe hath endued either with no Melt at all, or at leaſt with a very little one.</p>
                        <p>The continual Heat, which che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth the Heart, and warmeth the maſs of Blood, diſſolves all the ſubtileſt parts of the Seroſity into Vapours, and again Concocting the reſt [which by its frequent frying, and preſſing of the ſweet from the ſalt, I call the remaining Progeny] it would altogether turn it to Bile; Except the providence of Nature for the purging of the bitter Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or rather of Salt thickned by too much Concoction, had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the Body with a fit Emun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</p>
                        <p>And as Fullers uſe to colour their hands with thoſe Liquors they die with, ſo that Bilous Intral, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, according to the divers tinctures of Bile, either is yellowiſh red, or of a languiſhing aſh-colour, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times blackiſh green, or brown, though the Blood be exactly red.</p>
                        <pb n="168" facs="tcp:170048:91"/>
                        <p>Hence in the Child in the Womb, in which there is never any Chyle bred, about the beginning of its forming, the Liver hath its Saffron-colour'd <hi>Cystis</hi> full of Bile, though other waies the Blood be of a purple die: Which is an evident Argument, that the Bile is not the Excrement of the Second, as they call it, Concoction; but an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement of the Blood, which (Blood) is onely tranſmitted into the Liver of the Child in the Wombe.</p>
                        <p>Neither may be the fervid Blood in the Mother, and ſtrain'd by the Uterin Liver [the Lump] in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, ſhould in ſuch purity erre in the Veins of the Embryon, except it ſhould leave the greateſt part of it in the Liver, into the which it firſt floweth by the Coeunt Pipes of the Umbilick Veins.</p>
                        <p>And this, as I believe, is the Chief Office of the Liver in Living Creatures.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:170048:91"/>
                     <head>THE OBJECTIONS Anſwered.</head>
                     <p>WIll you ſo indeed, ſay you, exhauſt the whole Blood of its Bile by the diverting Coeliack Branch?</p>
                     <p>Before (Reader) I anſwer what I think, I will interrogate thy knowledge by viciſſitude in this place: Prethee tell me by what Engin the Blood, which at the ſame time enters the Iliack Arteries that it enters the Emulgent, doth iſſue its ſeroſity into the Reins? For that without doubt the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Nature appointed the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Blood's Circular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that through divers periods at laſt the whole Blood might ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed into the ſame Inns.</p>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:170048:92"/>
                     <p>Again, you demand, by what means this Tranſcolation is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; and how it cometh to paſs, that thoſe paſſages pervious to the Bile, exclude the <hi>Serum</hi> and Blood: Neither they on the other ſide are patent to the Bile which admit the <hi>Serum?</hi> whether becauſe the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> is more ſubtill than the Bile? or otherwiſe?</p>
                     <p>I confeſs the Cauſe of ſo great a wonder is hid from me, if you will not admit for a ſufficient reaſon the diverſity of Figures which is in the ſtraining bodies, and in the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Colon.</p>
                     <p>In vain wilt thou endeavour to put a Triangle of the ſame altitude with the Diameter of a round hole, into it, or into a three-angled hole a Quadrangle, or ſome other many Angled Figure: And I ſhall eaſily ſuffer my ſelf to be perſwaded, that the ſame kind of Figures is not found in Aqueous Parts which is found in Bilous; and that therefore the Bile [at leaſt that which is moſt groſs]
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170048:92"/>being unfitting to the paſſages of the Reins, cannot retire thither; As neither can the thicker ſeroſity, for the ſame diſcommodities enter into that Province which is onely proper to the Bile.</p>
                     <p>But if thou demand, whether or no there be Figures in the moſt ſmalleſt particles of Bile or Water.</p>
                     <p>I will anſwer firſt, That the Water is not onely a porous body, but likewiſe cavernous with many Figures of pores. The Learned <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> hath demonſtrated this with great ſagacity. But in vain ſhall the diverſity of Figures be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted into the Aqueous Pores, which diverſity thou denieſt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in thoſe parts whereof the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſiſts. But that there was diverſity of Figures in the Pores of the Water, <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> proved by a Noble Experiment.</p>
                     <p>He threw a Meaſure of common Salt into Spring Water; the Water within a ſhort time did onely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve a certain part of this, the reſt
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170048:93"/>of the Salt remaining untouched. In the ſame VVater Nitre being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd, a part of it did by melting mix it ſelf with the VVater, a part remained undiſſolv'd. Thirdly, by the ſame a part of Allom diſſolved, a part remained whole. Fourthly, <hi>Sal Amoniack</hi> tryed the ſame For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, with others, which by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves he had mixed with the VVater.</p>
                     <p>As I think you may alſo expreſs the Figures of melted Salt in that VVater which is commonly call'd <hi>Stygian,</hi> or <hi>Aqua Fortis,</hi> and the waies of diſſolving Metals in the ſame.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Aqua Fortis</hi> is of two ſorts; One, call'd <hi>Common,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves all Metals except Gold; The other, call'd <hi>Regia,</hi> reduces their King to Powder; Silver neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs therein reſerving his Figure with unſpotted Conſtancy, ſcorning the Pride of ſuch a prerogative.</p>
                     <p>The Matter of the <hi>Common</hi> is the Spirits of Vitriol, Nitre, &amp; Sea-ſalt.</p>
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:170048:93"/>
                     <p>This becomes <hi>Regia,</hi> if you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnate it with as much <hi>Sal Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack</hi> as it can diſſolve. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as I think, can the <hi>Common</hi> make impreſſion in Gold, becauſe the figured little Bodies of theſe Spirits do ſo exactly fit the Golden Pores, that flopping their motion, they reſt within the Metall. It diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves the reſt either with its Fire, or with the Sulphur which is in Metals arroding with the ſharp points of their Figures the divers Cavities of the Metallick Pores, whilſt they contend to be admitted into the fellowſhip of thoſe fitter to them; I had almoſt ſaid, bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering down the Cavities: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Sal Ammoniack,</hi> mixed with theſe Salts, doth agree with the Pores of Silver, but no waies with with thoſe of Gold, it firſt occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieth the Silver Pores, ſo that it quieteth the invaſion of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, whom it ſtirreth up againſt Gold, the VVall being demoliſhed, and admits them deſiring it.</p>
                     <pb n="174" facs="tcp:170048:94"/>
                     <p>If thou have any other Cauſe of theſe Events, Reader, different from the Figures of the Aqueous Pores, and thoſe which determine the Salts and their Spirits, prethee commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate it to our knowledge.</p>
                     <p>Truly the quadrat ſpace of the Pores ſhall be ſo fill'd with the wonted quadrature of Sea-ſalt, as their ſix-corner'd profundity ſhall be poſſeſs'd with hexaedron ſolidity of the points of Nitre.</p>
                     <p>The ſame judgement is to be given of the Figures of the reſt of the Salts.</p>
                     <p>If Bile, which we acknowledged to be Salt mixt with a certain Oilous humour, be mixt with <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> it ſalts it: and the Urine is in ſo much more brackiſh, as there is more Bile mixt with it: And if the abundance of Bile exceed the diſſolving force of the VVater, whatſoever remains, being rolled up in Cryſtalline Sand, and like Salt, fuſi'e by Fire under it, 'tis juſt it ſhould ſettle in the bottome. Hot VVater will contain more
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170048:94"/>Salt mixt with it than Cold VVater will, <hi>viz.</hi> the Fire enlarging its Pores by reaſon of the fellowſhip of the Air contain'd there, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily rarified.</p>
                     <p>VVhence, ſeeing there is neither Guts nor Cavities promiſcuous to the Bile and <hi>Serum,</hi> neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous diverticles, but ſeeing that onely of the Bile floweth out to the Urine, which being moſt ſubtill in the maſs of Blood, is moſt fit to tincture the Urine; ſo neither doth the groſſeſt of the <hi>Serum</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate into the Gall, but that onely that can lubricate the way, and in which the Bile can flow; it will not therefore be amiſs to admit in both Bile, <hi>viz.</hi> and <hi>Serum,</hi> diverſity of Figures.</p>
                     <p>I ſaid the moſt ſubtill: For the Bile is not of one onely conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; Yea I think it three-fold, and that to be moſt ſubtill which being mixt together with the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> avoydeth with the Urine.</p>
                     <p>The other two ſorts is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170048:95"/>by the Liver; That which is more ſubtill, entreth the Gall; The other, of more groſs juice, poſſeſſeth the Hepatick Paſſage; The out-flowing of both may be moveth the inmoſt Tunicle of the Inteſtins, both of them diſcharge the duty of natural Clyſters, and being mixed with the Excrements, are evacuated.</p>
                     <p>So the variety of the Searcher-like paſſages, and the divers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figurations of ſtraining. Bodies, doth in this place ſtop the paſſage of fluid things, but in that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows it. Hence the Urine, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Bile, paſſeth through the Reins into the Bladder, I mean that which is ſubtilleſt in the maſs of Blood; The Acidity goeth to nouriſh the Melt; The Subtiller Bile floweth out of the Liver into the Gall, the Groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer running into the Hepatick Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. I will ſay in a word, That the Excrements can take up
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170048:95"/>their Inns by the Gates onely appointed for them, the Poſterns of others being altogether ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Mundus regitur Opinionibus.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
